Log on, gem!
Log on, gem!
Let me present to you...
Let me present to you...
the famous RPC Sóng M alguien
the famous RPC Sóng M alguien
from Hanyang in Pohbank
from Hanyang in Pohbank
Episode 14
Episode 14
Please welcome Mr.P Hong Xœ bother ASL
Please welcome Mr.P Hong Xœ bother ASL
Teacher, Academician Wang and all the guests
老師 王院士 還有各位來賓
Colleagues in the hospital, good night everyone
院內的同仁 大家晚安
It is a great pleasure to invite Professor Chen Zhuting today
今天很高興來邀請陳竹庭教授
Come give knowledge Try this speech
來給知識 想驗這個演講
Professor Chen's Basic Experience
陳教授的基本的經歷
in the speech
在演講稿上都有
But I can reveal a lot.
不過我可以爆料 爆很多的料
Because he and I are colleagues at National Taiwan University
因為我跟他在台大是同事
20 years
20幾年
his office is next door to mine
他的辦公室就在我的辦公室隔壁
So I have worked with you for many years
所以同事了很多年
he is very easy to recognize
他是非常容易被認得的
when you speak
等於你們演講的時候
it's his hair
就是他的頭髮
then very elegant
然後很飄逸
Then
然後
We are the Beethoven of chemistry
我們是化學界的貝多芬
You can see her image is very similar to that photo of Beethoven
你看她的影像就跟貝多芬的那個照片很像
so you'll remember
所以你會記得起來
That Mr. Chen
那個陳老師
National Taiwan University is mine
台大是我的
He is my student in the chemistry department
在化學系是我的學弟
Then after going abroad
然後出國以後
Go to Emerging Natti University
去新興納提大學
And Ai Hehua
還有愛河華
Ph.D. from State University
State University拿的博士
Then did a postdoc at Penn State
然後在賓州做了博士後
Returned to National Taiwan University to teach in about 1985
大概在85年回到台大認教
in teaching
在教學方面
very popular with students
很受學生的歡迎
Research is also well done
研究也做得很出色
Received the Outstanding Research Award from the National Science Council
有拿過國科會的傑出研究獎
In recent years very
最近幾年非常
This cares about the general education of the university
這個關心大學的通識教育啦
science education
科學教育啦
so this
所以這個
also did this
也當過這個
The director of the chemistry center of the entire Taiwan chemical community
整個臺灣化學界化學中心的這個主任
And now this is National Taiwan University
然後現在是臺大的這個
Science Education Development Center
科學教育發展中心
He put a small one outside
那個他在外頭放了一個小的那個
Panford
Panford
that
那個
Science Education Development Center
科學教育發展中心
he puts a lot of effort
他著力很多
that is now
那現在已經是
Uh, for example, his Discovery series
呃譬如說他的探索系列
Already the seventh installment of the Discovery series
已經是第七期的探索系列
This exploration series is very fun
這個探索系列很好玩就是
Uh, there are about six long and eight long in one semester.
呃一學期大概有有六長八長左右的
weekend speech
周末演講
Music Institute at National Taiwan University
在臺大的音力所
Music Institute of National Taiwan University
臺大的音力所
This weekend from two to four
這個周末從兩點到四點
something like this
跟這個有點像
then no credit
然後也沒有學分
I don't care about the guests
也跟客人不關心
But the students participated enthusiastically
但是學生都參加得很踴躍
It's like there were 400 people last time
也都是好像上一次有400個人
When the classroom is full, the outside is also full
教室做滿 外頭也都做滿
This is what he promotes. This year is the seventh issue of the exploration series.
這都是他推動的今年是第七期的探索系列
So you know he puts a lot of effort into
所以你就知道他花很大的心力
On the development of science education
在這個科學教育發展上頭
I think he will have his own characteristics when he comes on stage
我想等會他上台就有他的特色
easily you will remember him later
很容易以後你就會記得他
All Taiwanese high school teachers
所有的台灣的高中老師
Everyone in Taiwan remembers him as a very special
台灣都記得他這個非常特別的
unique style
unique的風格
This year he will also talk about a very unique topic
今年他也要講一個非常unique的題目
Energy and Sustainable Civilization
能源跟永續文明
We clap hands to welcome Professor Chen
我們拍手 歡迎陳教授
Thanks
謝謝
Thank you Vice President Peng
謝謝彭副院長
This is really unreasonable
這個實在是很不敢當
He does have an office next door to mine
他的確是辦公室在我隔壁
So I have been the care of Vice President Peng for so many years
所以我這麼多年來都是彭副院長的照顧
I'm going to this precious place today
今天要到這個貴寶地
I really feel a little bit like selling articles in front of Confucius
實在是有一點點覺得在孔夫子面前賣文章
Especially vice president Peng will fly to Europe tonight
尤其是彭副院長今天晚上就要大飛機到歐洲去
I really feel a little unworthy
我實在覺得有點不敢當
Then he specially invited Academician Wang Yi over to say
然後又特別把王議院士請過來說
The following Q&A and the ending part should be annoyed to Academician Wang Yi
後面的Q&A和結尾的部分要偏惱王議院士
So two good colleagues and good friends can come here today
所以兩位好同事好朋友能夠今天過來
let myself be a little pampered
讓我自己也有一點受寵落精
Of course, I rarely feel nervous when I give a speech.
當然也是很少我演講的時候會覺得緊張
I just mentioned it to Professor Tang Pingzhe
剛剛跟湯平哲教授我才特別提到
So here's a lot of familiar faces I've seen
所以這邊有我已經看到有很多的熟面孔
Colleagues, good friends of Zhongyuan Institute
同仁們這個中原院的好朋友
Hello everyone
同仁們大家好
And good night, viewers
然後各位觀眾們大家晚安
Thanks
謝謝
I actually struggled for a long time
我其實掙扎了很久
I have been thinking about what kind of topic to use for this speech
是一直在考慮到底用什麼樣的題目來做這個演講
It's a feast of knowledge, I know we should talk about something more popular
是知識饗宴我知道應該要談比較普及性一點的東西
But if you want to enter Academia Sinica
可是要進中研院的話
I always feel that it is better to have a little professionalism behind
我總覺得要有一點專業在後面比較好
But I still chose this topic
可是我後來還是選了這個題目
Express my recent concerns
表示我最近比較關心的問題
Some have gone beyond chemistry
有些已經跨到化學的外面去了
Although Ren Yuan still has a very close relationship with chemistry
雖然仁元他仍然跟化學的關係是非常緊密的掛鉤的
But in what I'm going to report today
可是在後面的我今天要報告的內容裡頭
You can see that many but not all of the questions I asked were
你們可以看到我提出來的問題很多不全部是
Especially most likely not chemistry problems
尤其大部分可能不是化學的問題
If I continue, I will give lectures related to chemistry
如果繼續我要講化學的相關的演講的
maybe please include
可能請包含一下
The other is that sustainable civilization is actually a question that is often raised by people nowadays.
另外一個是永續文明其實是現在常常大家提出的問題
Then I want to emphasize a little bit to everyone.
那我特別要跟大家稍微強調一下
After all, when a scientist looks at something like this
到底一個科學家在看這樣的事情的時候
Do you have any unique perspectives?
有沒有一些比較獨特的觀點
The crisis for everyone is now whether domestic or foreign
人人危機是現在國內也好 國外也好
A question that everyone pays close attention to
大家通都非常注意的問題
but there is a problem in taiwan
不過在台灣有一個麻煩
As long as it is a very hot topic or problem
只要是非常熱的議題或者是問題
Then everyone will find a self-shooting answer to it.
那大家就會把它找出一個自射答案出來
Then everyone is very familiar with this thing, we have all heard of it
然後大家就很熟悉的說 這個東西我們通通都聽過了
In fact, is everyone’s crisis really serious in Taiwan?
其實人人危機在台灣是不是真的是很嚴重
I believe this question is not so easy to answer
我相信這個問題也不是那麼容易回答
But let's see if you go to Crisis Encyclopedia to find the definition
可是讓我們看一下你如果去危機百科上面去找一下定義的話
Everyone's crisis actually refers to when your personnel, especially in terms of economics, he emphasized
人人危機其實是提到說當你的人員尤其他強調在跟經濟面上
When you have difficulties in working needs
你有了工需上的困難的時候
He has bottleneck congestion
他有瓶頸的擁塞現象
We already said he can use crisis
我們就已經說他是能用危機了
I remember myself paying more attention to this noun
我記得我自己比較注意到這個名詞
It happened to be when I first came to America
是我剛好第一次剛到美國的時候
At that time, cars were also expensive, and gasoline was also expensive.
那個時候汽車也貴了 油也貴了
Then all the graduate students suddenly couldn't find a job
然後所有畢業同學一下子很多都找不到事情了
So it's obviously not just this that Yong shot
所以雍射的顯然也不只是這個
ordinary economic problems
普通的經濟問題而已
But what everyone feels more easily recently should be
可是大家最近更容易感覺到的應該是
In terms of interesting electricity prices, oil prices,
在趣味性的電價 油價這些方面
Immediately it has been reflected that it will rise
馬上已經反映出來要上漲
For Taiwan, everyone has been arguing a lot lately
這個對台灣來講 大家最近吵得很兇
If you look at this table
你如果看這一張表
Is an Exon XN in the US their oil company
是美國的一個Exon XN他們的石油公司
A report given in 2004
在2004年給的一個報告
This is the 2004 report
這是2004年的報告
It is above the work area, the green area
它在工區上面來講 綠色的這一塊
Already seen in 2004
在2004年的時候 已經可以看到
that is to say they are
就是說他們在
In terms of the output that can be provided
能夠提供的產量上面來講
Already in a downward trend
已經是在走下坡路往下減少的趨勢
But
可是
The world's demand is going up in reverse
全世界的需求量反而是反向的往上走
This is 2004
這個是2004年
you can tell
你可以看得出來
They think the difference between supply and demand
他們認為供需的差別
Already at least 4% to 6%
已經起碼有4%到6%
The gap above this
這個以上的差距
So far, 2012 is obviously in
到現在的話2012顯然在
Here you can see the gap increase
這邊你可以看到這個差距的增加
is multiplied several times
是用幾倍的增加的
Indicates the current situation of personnel crisis
表示現在人員危機的狀況
Compare
比
In the past few years, the difference is much more
前幾年差別又多了很多
So we use another table to look at the oil price and see that the oil price is actually what he just uploaded
所以我們用另外一張表來看油價看這個油價是事實上他剛上傳的
oil price
油價來算
This is a more professional way of saying we don't care about him
這比較專業的說法我們不就不管他
You can see it in this trend
你可以看在這個趨勢裡頭
This one is the most obvious and it was two years ago
這一個是最明顯的也就是兩年前的
economic tsunami
經濟海嘯
caused by
所造成的
Oil prices per barrel break through
油價每一桶衝破了
$140
140美元
That
那
Actually it's probably closer to 150
事實上大概接近接近了150
So this signal is very obvious
所以這一個訊號是非常明顯的
But what I am asking everyone to pay attention to now is not just this signal.
可是我現在請大家注意的不是這一個訊號而已
but from 2003
而是從2003年開始
Until now about 2012
到現在大概2012年
Its overall trend is to run upwards
它整個趨勢是往上跑的
And looking back
而且往後面看的情況
it doesn't need another pick
它不需要再來一個pick
it directly this number
它直接的這個數字
might break through
可能就會往上衝破
More than 140 or even 150 U.S. barrels
超過140甚至150美桶美元
so in a short time
所以時間在很短的時間之內
such a rise
這樣子的上漲
This is why our
這是為什麼我們的
My senior, Vice President Peng's junior
我的學長彭副院長的學弟
Minister of Xie Enxiang Yuan
謝恩祥院的部長
It was the first class in Takao's class in the Department of Chemical Medicine
是排大化醫系高尾一屆的
you see obviously he has a headache
你看顯然他很頭痛
In fact, it should be our headache.
其實事實上應該是我們頭痛才對
Because this is at least a 10% increase
因為這個起碼有10%的增加
is about to see
是馬上要看得到的
So these two slides show
所以這兩張投影片看得出來
Equal to the crisis is a problem all over the world
等於危機在全世界都是一個難題
But I think there is one more important thing
不過我想更重要一件事情
In fact, it is for Taiwan
事實上它對台灣來講
Might be a big problem too
可能也是一個大難題
There is an important reason is
有一個重要的原因是
Taiwan actually has almost no natural energy
台灣其實幾乎沒有天然的能源
That looks tricky
那這個樣子棘手的問題
If we all rely on the outside
我們如果全部要靠外面的話
what to do next
往下要做怎麼辦
Of course, from the perspective of economic development
當然以經濟發展的角度來看
this is a problem
這是一個難題
this is my first question
這是我提出的第一個問題
I may ask a lot of questions today
今天我可能提出不少的問題
In fact, I will not provide an answer
其實我都不會提供解答
I'm thinking
我在想
All our people and experts in Taiwan
我們台灣所有的人民和專家
should all come face to face with us
都應該來共同面對我們
things to face
要面對的事情
I have a lot of stories to tell today
今天我有很多的故事要講
The first one I talked about is Easter Island in the Pacific
第一個我就談到太平洋的復活島
This is Glass Muscia
這是玻璃泥夕亞
in the Pacific Ocean
整個在太平洋的海域裡頭
the easternmost island
最東邊的一個小島
In such a big cloud head
在這麼大的一個土雲頭
it's actually invisible
它其實是看不見的
Taiwan can be found in this place at least on the map
台灣在這個地方至少地圖上還找得到
Actually Easter Island is closer
事實上復活島更接近
South America so actually belongs to Chile
南美洲 所以事實上屬於智利
such a small island
這麼小的一個島嶺頭
its most special thing
它最特別的一件事情
is it along all the coastlines
就是它沿著所有的海岸線
There are many people's head portraits standing
有許許多多的人頭像站的
Some are standing to watch the sunrise
有些是站的看日出
Some are standing to watch the sunset
有些是站的看日落
So often a whole row by the sea
所以常常一整排的在海邊
You can see this giant stone statue
你可以看到這種巨石頭像
been full for a while
早就滿有一段時間
more than a hundred years
上百年以上的時間
It's because everyone doesn't know why it looks like this
是大家不知道為什麼有這樣子的像
will be there
會在那個地方
Of course this gives us Taiwan
當然這就給了我們台灣
Especially the key report of Taiwan
尤其是台灣的關鍵報告
such programs
這類的節目
one of my life's big wishes
我生平的一個大願望之一
just hold a new event
就是辦一個新的活動
The new program called Non-Critical Reports
叫做新的節目叫做非關鍵報告
They said this thing was visited by aliens
他們說這個東西什麼外星人來過
What has been what a ladder
什麼有過什麼一梯
What did the visit say a lot
造訪什麼講了一大堆
This island is actually quite special.
這個島其實還真的蠻特別
Because when the Europeans went to the island
因為在歐洲人到島上去的時候
They're actually a lost island
他們其實已經是一個沒落的島嶼
But a few hundred years ago
可是再往前幾百年的話
he used to have a coconut tree for the restaurant
他曾經有過餐廳的椰子樹
It is better than the one from National Taiwan University
是比台灣大學的那個
And there is this so-called great prince in the Central Plains Court
和有中原院裡頭的這個所謂的大王爺
taller coconut tree
還要高的椰子樹
the whole island is coconut grove
是整個島上是椰林
It's really a forest of coconut trees
就是真的是椰子樹的森林
you can see the back of this
你可以看到這個後面
almost photogenic
幾乎是光突突的
So its decline and the change of resources on it
所以它的沒落跟它上面的資源的改變
In fact, it has a lot to do with
事實上是有很大的關係的
Another thing is that the Maya of America
另外一件事情是美洲的馬雅
This is another place where aliens have been
這是另外一個外星人到過的地方大概
OK
OK
We still have a few places that we can look at one by one
我們還蠻有幾個地方是可以一個一個看
words of aztec civilization
阿茲特克文明的話
from the thirteenth century to the seventeenth century
是差不多在十三世紀到十七世紀
you can see their temple of the sun
你可以看到他們的太陽神殿
In fact, there are many pyramids in Egypt.
其實跟埃及的金字塔有很多
There is a little specific flavor
有那麼一點具體而為的味道
In fact, there are movies that have already been filmed
事實上現在有電影都已經拍到
In fact, they often do restricted activities when they go up.
他們這個上去其實是常常是要做限制的活動
But the whole building feels very modern
可是整個的建築是感覺上非常現代的
That is to say they are very primitive looking although limited in activity
也就是說他們雖然限制的活動是看起來非常的原始
Many places in their buildings actually seem to be related to mathematics
他們建築的很多地方其實好像跟數學的關係
In fact, there is also an astronomical relationship.
事實上還有天文的關係 落干復合
Composite is pretty good
復合的相當的不錯
This is actually not very strange
這其實也並不是很稀奇
Because a building like this is actually a human tool
因為像這樣子的建築它事實上是屬於人類的工具
Human tools without support from mathematics and physics
人類的工具在沒有數學和物理支持的情況之下
By experience, people have had a long time
靠著經驗 人已經有滿長的時間
Can show very brilliant achievements in architecture
可以在建築上表現出非常輝煌的成績
Of course, in addition to that, they are full of special
當然除此之外他們還有滿特別的是
They have some special astrological characters
他們有一些滿特殊的象星文字
These astrological characters are comparisons
這些象星文字都是比較
early travel
早期出行一點的
Comparing text that is not a monogram
比較不屬於單字型的文字
Now many of them have been revealed
現在有很多都已經能夠揭馬了
It can be seen that this civilization
可以看得出來這個文明
In fact, it has its degree of brilliance
其實它有它一定輝煌的程度
Of course, including some of their statues
當然也包括了他們一些的雕像
These statues are even more
這些雕像就更使得
There are many key reports that are full of words.
關鍵報告很多講得口不恨非了
The other one in Blue America is the Inca civilization
藍美洲另外一個是印加文明
exactly in central america and blue america
正好在中美洲和藍美洲
The timing of the two shaking echoes is not very consistent
兩個搖搖呼應的時間不是太一致
this is a little later
這個稍微晚一點
Around the 15th, 40th and 16th centuries
大概在15、40到16世紀
It was later wiped out by the Europeans
後來被歐洲人滅掉了
Inca kingdom it's actually a very special one
印加王國它事實上很特殊的一個
It's on the hills of Kalamahah
是在卡拉馬哈的山上面
There are very high mountains with very delicate buildings
有非常的高的山上面有非常精緻的建築
Inside this exquisite building
這種精緻的建築裡頭
Including very complex irrigation facilities and
包括了很複雜的灌溉的設施和
The constructed system
所建構出來的系統
These systems are very
這些系統都是非常地
researched a lot
研究的非常的多了
In about National Geographic
在大概National Geographic
is the country's first magazine
就是國家第一雜誌
it already has a lot of videos
它已經有很多的影片
can introduce
可以來介紹
How are these buildings made?
到底它們這些建築是怎麼樣做的
is a very detailed building
是非常細緻的建築
talking about this
談到這個的話
This is one of the reasons why I am interested
這個是引起我興趣的原因之一
I probably will today
我今天大概會
not the first time
不是第一次
I will mention it a few times later
我後面還會有幾次要提到
the representatives such a person
這個代表們這樣一個人
because the man he wrote the basic book
因為這個人他寫的基本書
in my recent years
在我最近這幾年
When the general education courses offered by Taiwan University at the beginning of the year
台灣大學年頭開的通識課的時候
have used his book
已經用到了他的書
as a textbook
作為教科書
because answered me some
因為回答了我一些
very important question
蠻重要的問題
This is a thicker book
這一本是比較厚的一本
called Clares
叫Clares
Chinese translation into big collapse
中文翻成大崩壞
Should be China Times
應該是中國時報
The times see what they say
時報就看他們說
Times Publishing is their book
時報出版是他們所出的書
This one should have won a Pulis Award
這一本應該也得過普利斯獎
His book is called Da Bang Huai
他的書是叫大崩壞
Another word to repeat
另外一個復提的話
in a society
就是一個社會裡頭
how to choose
到底怎麼樣去選擇
whether they succeed or fail
他們是成功還是失敗
I believe no society
我相信沒有一個社會
Will hope to choose to go down the road of failure
會希望要選擇往失敗的路上走
But at the end
可是居然到最後的時候
Why are they such a brilliant civilization
他們為什麼那麼輝煌的文明
unsustainable
無以為繼
can't continue
不能夠繼續
these splendid civilizations
這些這麼輝煌的文明
What kind of mistake did you make?
到底是犯了什麼樣的錯誤
Or encountered some kind of scourge
或者碰到了什麼樣的天譴
make them suffer
使得他們遭遇這樣子的事情
sorry
對不起
another question i want to ask
另外一個問題我要問的
that is
就是說
in every society
每一個社會裡頭
We know that in modern terms
我們知道照現代來看的話
The average IQ is about the same
平均智商大概都差不多
But why some civilizations
可是為什麼有一些的文明
in a world
在一個世界上
role played today
今天所扮演的角色
There are particularly prominent places
有格外突出的地方
Is it true that in some societies
到底是不是有些社會裡頭
Its collective intelligence is higher
它的集體智慧比較高呢
collective intelligence
那這樣的集體智慧
there is a higher place
有比較高的地方
Is the difference in height a personal material inside?
高低之差是不是裡面的個人的材質
There is a difference between the average and the high and low
平均也有高低之差呢
What kind of society is it that reaches some consensus
到底是怎麼樣一個社會它達成一些共識
make them make decisions that lead to death
使他們做的決定有些是去向於滅亡
Some are destined for greater glory
有些是去向於更加的輝煌
So if you see our Taiwan Legislative Yuan
所以如果看到我們台灣的立法院的話
You will wonder why a group of
你就會好奇為什麼一群
It stands to reason that smart people will work together to make some
照道理應該很聰明的人會在一起做一些
stupid thing
還蠻笨的事情
For many years their names were worn on their vests
很多年他們的名字都穿在他們的背心上面
So we don't have to figure out who it is.
所以我們也不必去指出來到底是誰了
Fortunately, this is in the Legislative Yuan
這個好在是在立法院
If this kind of thing happened in college
這種事情如果發生在大學的話
This problem becomes serious
這個問題就變嚴重了
So in my speech today
所以我今天的演講裡頭
Its outline will probably be discussed from several different projects
它的大綱大概會從幾個不同的項目來談
Maybe it's because I'm a scientist personally
也許是因為我個人是一個科學家的緣故
I will definitely learn from the energy in the universe and nature
我一定會從宇宙以及自然界裡頭的能量
talk about these things
這些事情來談
Yes and then of course it will soon cut to life and human
是然後當然很快的就要切到生命和人類的
go inside the circle
圈子裡頭去
love with people
跟人緣情
In fact, it is closely related
其實是細細相關的
And the development of every civilization
而每一個文明的發展
It's all about popularity
都跟人緣有關係
I'm not actually very detailed
我其實並沒有非常細緻的
Let's talk about the details
去談人緣的細節
because of our problem
因為我們的問題
will focus on popularity and sustainable civilization
會集中在人緣和永續文明上面
this photo is very famous
這張照片非常的有名
It's Apollo 17
是Apollo 17號
in may be
在可能是
late 60's
60年代的末期
Photos taken when I went to space
到太空去的時候照到的照片
This one may be so far
這張可能是到目前為止
Photos of Earth are referenced
地球的照片都被引用了
one of the most pictures
最多的照片之一
you can see the arabian peninsula very clearly
你可以看到非常清楚的阿拉伯半島
and the region from Africa all the way to Antarctica
以及非洲一直到南極的區域
is very clear
是看得非常清楚的
in history
在歷史上
not too many people have a chance
不是有太多的人有機會
able to see the landscape like this
能夠看到這樣子的景觀
see our hometown
把我們的家鄉看到
The entire spherical shape can be seen very clearly
整個球狀的看得非常清楚
But if we look at it historically
可是如果要從歷史上去看的話
this Heraclitus
這個赫拉克利圖斯
In fact strictly speaking
事實上嚴格來講
These are more philosophers
這些都比較算哲學家
i don't think we will
我想我們不會
treat them as scientists
把它們當作科學家
when he was in greek times
他在希臘時代的時候
sorry over here
這邊對不起
not very clear
不是很清楚了
Should be BC
應該是西元前
Around the fifth or sixth century
大概五世紀到六世紀的時候
He already mentioned one thing
他就已經提出來一件事情說
The world is actually a combination of many states
這個世界其實是很多的狀態組合成的
And between these states and states
而這些狀態和狀態之間
In fact, it has a rheological change
其實它有一種流變的變化發生
his famous saying
他很有名的一句話
He said every morning a new sun rises
他說每天早上都有新的太陽升起來
So he said fire is the source of all matter
所以他說火是所有物質的源頭
That is, in Greece from about the third century to the fifth century
也就是在希臘的大概第三世紀到第五世紀
people kept coming out and saying
不停地開始有人出來說
this world
這個世界
The very rich and diverse landscapes we see
我們看到的這些非常豐富多元不同的景觀
In fact, there are very simple elements
其實是有很簡單的元素
Telus was first proposed
最早提出來是Telus
he said it was water
他說是水
But the green map master Herac said
不過赫拉克綠圖師是說的
He said it should be fire
他說應該是火
when going from his point of view
從他的觀點去的時候
lead to later clark
引到後來的克拉克
sorry it should be
對不起 應該是
I forgot the name
這個名字我一下忘掉了
And then there's Aristotle, he's talking about the four elements
後面是阿亞里斯多德 他在說的四大元素
Your boss said he included fire as a key element.
你頭頭的話 他就把火列入了一個關鍵的元素
But if it is in our modern times
可是如果是在我們的近代的話
You saw a very important telescope in the 90s
你在90年代看到有一個很重要的望遠鏡
NASA put it in the sky
有NASA放到天上去
We call it the Hubble Telescope because it's a memorial
我們把稱作哈伯望遠鏡 因為他是紀念
The one who said the universe is expanding
說宇宙是在膨脹的那一位
haber mentioned his name
哈伯所提他的名字
as the name of the telescope
當作望遠鏡的名字
When it was put up, there were several kinds of lenses on it.
放上去的時候他上面有好幾種的鏡頭
X-ray lens included Infrared lens included Ultraviolet lens included
包括了X光鏡頭 包括了紅外線鏡頭 紫外線光鏡頭
There are a lot of telescopic lenses on it
有很多的望遠鏡頭放上去
In fact, when I first put it on, it seemed that one of the lenses was broken.
其實剛放上去的時候好像還有一個鏡頭是壞掉的
So the space shuttle was sent up to recalibrate it.
所以還派了太空梭上去 把它重新校正過
replaced with a new one
換了一片新的
This is a very important tool
這是非常重要的一個工具
Since the family is slightly used in
自從家庭略放用在
After seeing the moons next to Jupiter with a telescope four hundred years ago
在四百年前用望遠鏡看到了木星旁邊的衛星以後
After putting this on
這個放上去之後
What he saw turned out to be a very different landscape
他所看到的結果是一個截然不同的景觀
Because of its Scope
因為它的Scope
We emphasize that this Scope is a field of vision
我們強調這個Scope是一個視野
It actually works on a telescope
它其實用放在望遠鏡上的話
Telescope is the field of view circled
Telescope 就是圈出來的那個視野
is right in the distance
是對在遠方的
This is exactly the same as Microscope, which is a microscope.
這個剛好跟Microscope也就是顯微鏡
The field of view it circles is placed in a very close distance.
它圈出來的視野是放在很近的距離裡頭
is a very different thing
是截然不同的事情
Scientists choose Scope
科學家選擇Scope
That is, our eyes are chosen
也就是選定了我們的眼睛
see what the target above
看到了什麼樣的目標上面
makes us use the special method
使得我們用到特殊的方法
special tools see special things
特殊的工具可以看到特殊的事物
This is a very important thing in the development of science
這個在科學發展裡頭是非常重要的一件事情
The results provided
所提供出來的結果
In fact, the one that proves that the universe is expanding is called
事實上是證明了宇宙在膨脹的一個叫做
The so-called Big Bang theory of the explosion
爆炸的所謂大霹靂的理論
you can tell
你可以看得出來
We actually see pictures made of galaxies and clouds
我們其實看到星系和雲氣造出來的圖片
like fragments after an explosion
就像爆炸以後的碎片
fly away form
向外飛離的形式
Such proof is actually not enough
這樣的證明其實還是不夠的
Another fact seen
另外一個看到的事實上
is the whole universe
是整個宇宙
it's actually in the process of exploding
它事實上在爆炸的過程之中
it's been a very long time
它經歷了一個非常長的時間
That is, the farthest light
也就是把最遠的光線
After collecting
收集過來了以後
We found that in fact the explosion time of the entire universe
我們發現其實整個宇宙的爆炸時間
has been carried over to a very precise number
已經延續了一個非常精確的數字
Relatively speaking, 13.7 billion years
相對來講的137億年
i remember when i was studying
我記得我在念書的時候
When studying in middle school and university
在中學大學念書的時候
The figure given at that time was about 10 billion to 15 billion
那時候給的數字大約是100億到150億
We already feel that it is not easy
我們已經覺得是不簡單
very precise number
非常精確的數字了
Now what Haberwang has told us is that
現在哈伯旺已經告訴我們的是
13.7 billion years
137億年的時間
during this time
在這段時間裡頭
In fact, there is a point of time
其實有一個時間的積點
Where is this plot in the space
這個積點是在空間的哪裡
not sure
不太清楚
But after a big bang
不過它經過了一個大爆炸以後
it keeps expanding
它就持續膨脹
Inflation is actually spread out over an almost flat universe
膨脹事實上是散佈在幾乎是一個平面的宇宙上面
The expansion process of the explosion is not linear yet.
那爆炸的膨脹過程還不是線性的
That is to say, it even has cases of accelerated expansion.
就是說它甚至還有加速膨脹的情況
That is, if you look at it from the present point of view
也就是以現在的眼光去看的話
The universe is actually still expanding
宇宙其實是在仍然在膨脹之中
But one important thing is
可是很重要一件事情是
if you push it back
如果你把它往回推的話
Its basis is in fact
它的基點事實上是
because it was a big bang
因為說是一個大爆炸
so it's a big energy
所以它是很大的一個能量
Transformation created matter after it exploded
轉換在爆炸了以後產生了物質
There is an interchanging state between man and matter
在人和物質之間有一個互變的狀態
for us now
對我們現在來講
Today's science we have been able to describe
今天的科學我們已經能夠描述
Our universe has many examples that make up it
我們的宇宙有很多的例子組成了它
There are many examples of pillows especially on the earth
枕頭尤其很多的例子在地球上也有
that is atoms
也就是原子
But if we look carefully
可是如果我們仔細去看的話
The universe is not what we imagined
這個宇宙不像我們想像的
It's really the same as our earth
真的都是跟我們的地球上一樣
There are many principles
有很多的原則而已
Main ingredient with wrinkle head
與皺紋頭的主要成分
Atomic substances are mainly pure and harmful elements
原子的物質主要是清和害兩種元素
If you have a little background in chemistry
如果說是對化學有一點點背景的
At least clear is one of the simplest elements
至少清是一個最簡單的元素
Hazard is an element slightly heavier than it
害是稍微比它重一點點的元素
But the combined weight of these two
可是這兩個加在一起的份量
Actually not many
其實不是很多的
If we list all the percentages
我們如果說把所有的百分比一列出來了以後
You can see the darker, black piece over here
你可以看到這邊比較深色的 黑色的這一塊
We now call it dark energy
我們現在稱它做暗能量
In other words don't know what kind of energy it is
換句話說不知道它是哪一種能量
Then here is the lighter black piece
然後這邊比較淺的黑的這一塊
is dark matter 30% 65%
是暗物質30% 65%
Together it makes up 95% of the universe
它加在一起已經占了宇宙的95%
That is 95% of the universe
也就是宇宙都有95%
we don't know what it is
我們不知道它是什麼東西
What we really know about Qing and Hari
我們真正知道的清和害
In terms of the scope it occupies
它所占的範圍來講的話
It's actually a very small part
其實是非常的少的部分
Of course there are some other elements that are less than Qinghe Harm
那當然還有比清和害更少的一些其他的元素
Let's look at it from here
我們從這一張頭去看
If you look at it, the part with the most cloud heads in the universe is called green
你看的話 宇宙雲頭最多的部分我們說是青
Blue accounts for 60% and black accounts for 36% or 37%
青占了60% 然後害占了36%或37%
Together it exceeds 95%
加在一起超過了95%
But this 95% is a relatively small amount in terms of the entire cosmic cloud head
可是這95%在整個宇宙雲頭來講是一個相對少量
Of course, the other part of us is not the same as on the earth.
當然我們另外的部分像地球上的話就不太一樣了
The most abundant part of the earth is actually iron
地球上含量最多的部分事實上是鐵
But most of the iron is in the center of the earth, not in the crust
可是鐵大部分是在地心裡頭 不是在地殼裡頭
If you look at it from the inside of the earth's crust
如果是從地殼裡頭去看的話
Its most part should be oxygen and then fine
它最多的部分應該是氧 然後是細
These are all different elements, which is what you must know when you study chemistry.
這個都是不同的元素 就是學化學的時候必須要知道的
But because there is a lot of water in our living body, more than 75% is water
可是在我們的生體裡頭因為有很多的水 75%以上是水
So you see, 65% is oxygen, and other words, blue accounts for 10%
所以你看 65%的是氧 然後其他的話青占了10%
So this together is mostly water
所以這個加在一起是大部分是水
But our body contains a lot of carbon
可是我們生體裡頭又含了很多的碳
So it means the part we are most familiar with
所以表示說我們最熟悉的部分
Including ourselves, including the earth we live on
包括我們自己 包括我們居住的地球
Everything is completely different from the environment outside our earth.
通通都跟我們地球外面的環境是截然不同的
Of course, if we look at it from the perspective of the entire universe
那當然如果說是把從整個宇宙的角度去看的話
We just said the transition from energy to matter
我們剛剛說從能量轉變成了物質
In fact, physicists are still spending a lot of effort to understand this process
這樣子的過程事實上物理學家還在花很大的力氣去了解它
However, there are some gradually more evidences showing that
不過有一些已經慢慢有比較多的證據顯示
There are actually a lot of clouds in Cosmos
宇宙紐其實有很多的雲氣
it actually has mass
它事實上是含有質量的
A phenomenon common to all matter is that it has mass
所有物質共通的一個現象就是都有質量
large or small mass
質量大或質量小
Although it is a small thing
雖然是質量很小的東西
If it's a lot, it still has a lot of gravity
如果它的量多了以後它仍然有很大的重力
It can be regarded as internal attraction, after being greedy and shrinking, it will produce scars
可以把它像內吸引 貪縮了以後它就會產生痕心
Therefore, a circle mark heart actually undergoes greed and shrinkage.
所以一個圓痕心事實上經過了貪縮了以後
it may become a scar
它就可能變成了一個痕心
But there are big and small scars
可是痕心有大的 有小的
If you look at it from the heart
如果以痕心來看的話
At its center, what actually happens is a nuclear reaction.
它的中心事實上發生的就是核反應
One of the two types of nuclear reactions is nuclear fission
核反應的兩種一種是核分裂
A kind of nuclear fusion
一種核融合來講的話
In fact it is because its content is mostly hydrogen
事實上它因為含量大部分是氫
So it's hydrogen atoms that produce nuclear fusion
所以是氫原子產生核融合
will form elements that slowly become comparisons
就會形成慢慢變成比較中的元素
If the star is big enough
如果這個恆星夠大的話
It goes through nuclear fusion like this
它經過這樣子的核融合
Over time it will become a red giant star
時間久了以後它會變成一個紅巨星
The red giant is actually at the end
紅巨星事實上到最後的時候
Its nuclear burn is very fast
它的核燃燒是非常的快速的
after such a rapid burn
在這樣子快速的燃燒以後
produces a lot of heavier elements
就產生了很多比較重的元素
when it dies
當它死掉的時候
there was a big bang
就發生一個大爆炸
Such explosions could produce superstars
這種爆炸就可能產生超星星
After this kind of superstar disperses the new elements around
這種超星星把新的元素散到了四周去以後
It may again form a new solar system
它又可能重新去形成一個新的太陽系
this is endless
這是循環不絕的
But if it is a smaller star
可是如果是比較小的恆星的話
when it has no chance of forming a red giant
它沒有機會形成紅巨星的時候
as soon as it goes to become a white dwarf
就已經一走到變成一個白矮星
so in fact
所以事實上
The ending may be different
結局有可能不太一樣
This is not my own professional field
這不是我本人的專業的範疇
But at least we can see a new sun every day
不過我們至少每天都可以看到一個新太陽
So when stars are in billions of years
所以恆星在幾十億年裡頭的時候
Our sun is actually five billion years old
我們的太陽事實上它已經有五十億年的
lifespan of about five billion years
大約五十億年的壽命
This lifespan is very close to the lifespan of the earth
這個壽命跟地球的壽命非常的接近
Earth's lifespan is currently estimated at 4.6 billion years
地球的壽命我們目前估計是四十六億年
It is estimated that our sun should have another five billion years to survive
估計我們的太陽應該還有五十億年的時間可以存活
So the earth doesn't actually have to worry about the sun's last time
所以地球其實也不必擔心太陽到最後的時候
Our sun will finally become a red giant star
我們的太陽也終於會變成一個紅巨星
Then the words of the leader throughout the planetary system
然後在整個行星系引頭的話
It is probably light and harmful is the main
它大概輕和害是主要的
But the other one percent is other elements
可是另外有百分之一的量是其他的元素
This is so important to us
這個對我們來講太重要了
because few things seem
因為看起來很少的東西
Instead, the rarest things around us
反而是我們周圍我們最稀有的東西
let's take a look
我們看一下
Let's go back and look at the previous one just now
剛剛前面一張我們再回頭去看一下
The last point is actually right
最後一點的話事實上正好
It was rice ear swallow 200 years ago
是200年前的稻耳吞
it raises an important concept
它提出來一個重要的概念
Because we just mentioned the name of the element
因為我們剛剛都提元素的名字
In fact every element
事實上每一種的元素
Its units are atoms
它的單位都是原子
Then if you have the same elements
那你如果元素相同的話
its atoms are the same
它的原子就是相同的
You if the elements are different
你如果元素不同的話
its atoms are different words
它的原子就是不同的話
This is what we started in middle school
這是我們在國中就開始
Atomic Blade
背的稻耳吞的原子刃
is what's inside
就是裡面的內容
things like this
像這樣子的事情
when already looking out
已經往外看的時候
Kiss is indeed the most swallowed element in the universe
親的確是宇宙吞頭最多的元素
Although we say that there are many things
雖然我們說有很多東西
something that is not an element
不是元素的東西
The proportion is quite high
占的比例還蠻高的
But if the already known elements swallow their heads
可是如果已經知道的元素吞頭來講的話
Kiss is still the most content
親到底還是含量最多的
At the same time it is also persevering
同時它也是恆心吞頭
main ingredient
主要的成分
I'm taking this time to tell you about this
我花這時間跟大家講這件事情
It is to let everyone experience one thing
是讓大家體會到一件事情
between energy and matter
能量和物質中間
The relationship is actually very close
關係其實非常的密切
What kind of environmental conditions is the problem
問題在什麼樣的環境條件
such as temperature or
譬如說溫度或是是
Kinetic energy of matter itself
物質本身的動能
enabling them to move between pools and people
使得它們能夠在池和人之間的
mutual change
互相的變化
In fact, speaking of chemistry
事實上對學化學來講的話
change between energy and matter
能量和物質之間的變化
it has very specific rules
它裡面有很特定的規則的
For example, if you look at it like a blue atom
譬如說像青原子來看的話
It has only one Naoko in the center
它的正中央只有一個直子
There will be an electron outside
外面會有一個電子
So we say that the blue atom has a direct son
所以我們說青原子是有一個直子
and an electron
和一個電子所組成的
but above the sun
可是在太陽上面的話
its son
它的直子
Two pairs of sons will be fused
兩對直子就會經過融合
in the process of fusion
在融合的過程之中
and many smaller examples
還會放出許多更小的例子
For example, neutrinos
譬如說微中子啊
Zhengzi
正子啊
A positron is the opposite of an electron
正子是跟電子相反的
The quality is the same as that of electrons
質量跟電子一樣
But electricity and electrons are just the opposite
可是電和跟電子剛好相反
It's on standby
是待陣電的
put something like this out
像這樣子的東西放出來
then it will generate
然後它就會產生
Naoko
原來都是直子
but neutrons
可是就會產生中子
After Naoko and Naoko got together
當中子跟直子接在一起了以後
it has the opportunity to generate new elements
它就有機會產生新的元素
so keep going down
所以繼續往下走
it becomes a practiced display
它變成一個所練習的展現
go down
往下走
It can even release Gama rays
甚至還可以放出 尬馬射線
so straight out
所以 直放出人
and then into a new substance
然後又變成新的物質
It can be harmful in the end
它到最後是可以產生 害和的
That is, throughout the development process
也就是在整個發展的過程之中
Although not achieved in one step
雖然不是 一步就達到的
But in the end we know that the sun is
可是到最後我們知道 太陽上是
Constant consumption is kinder
不停的消耗比較親切
Shouldn't it be kind, should it be pro-atomic?
應該不是應該說親切 應該說親原子
then produce harmful atoms
然後產生害原子
But there are other ways, dear, there are actually two
可是也有其他的方式 親事實上有兩種的
That is to say it has a finger
也就是說 它有一個指指
So it's a kiss but with a middle finger at the same time
所以就是親 可是同時帶有一個中指
This is what we call a knife
這個我們叫做刀
There is also a pointing
另外也是一個指指的
then there are two middle fingers
然後有兩個中指
As long as you have one pointing finger, it belongs to the relatives anyway.
你只要有一個指指的 反正都是屬於親類的東西
belonging to the same number of relatives
屬於親的同位數
If these two things collide
這兩個東西撞到一起去的話
It can also produce a harmful atom
它也可以產生一個害原子
Contains two middle fingers and two fingers
包括了兩個中指和兩個指指
That is, we can write it in chemical formula
也就是我們用化學式可以寫得出來
it can be harmful and
它可以產生害和
Situations like this happen every day
像這樣的情形是天天在
it happens on the sun
太陽上都會發生的
But in the part of its comparison
可是在它的比較裡面的部分的話
In fact there are some heavier elements
事實上就有一些比較重的元素
the heaviest sinks in the middle
最重的會陷到中間去
very little
量非常的少
But most of them are outside
可是比較多的是在外面的
Layer by layer, according to its density
一層一層其實按照它的密度
can be distinguished
是可以區分開來
So it can actually produce eggs
所以它其實可以產生蛋
can produce oxygen
可以產生氧
So we just mentioned
所以我們剛剛提到了
words at the center of the star
恆星的中心的話
If you go through nuclear fusion continuously
不斷的經過核融核的話
heavy elements will occur
重元素就會發生
So for example like a carbon atom
所以譬如說像碳原子
like nitrogen atom
像氮原子
In fact, if we continue to integrate
事實上再繼續融合下去的話
nitrogen atom followed by hydrogen atom
氮原子再跟氫原子
Fusion into oxygen atoms
融合成氧原子
So keep it up and you'll find
所以不停的它你就會發現
It has new elements coming out all the time
它一直有新的元素出來
see it this way
照這樣子去看
our solar system
我們的太陽系
should have been
應該以前
A sun has already exploded
已經有一個太陽爆炸過才對
into a super new system
變成了一個超新新的系統
and re-transform into one of our planetary systems
再重新轉變成一個我們的行星系的
It should be so
照道理應該是如此
so in this
所以在這個裡頭
the mystery of its energy
它的能量的奧密
just press
就是按
proposed
所提出來的
If you have to sacrifice a little material quality
如果你要犧牲到一點物質的質量
to generate energy
去產生能量的話
its often tiny mass
它常常極微小的質量
multiply by the speed of light
就可以乘上一個光速
That is, the square of an astronomical number
也就是一個天文數字的平方倍
make it produce huge lotus kernels
讓它產生巨大的荷仁
This kind of energy is very large
這種的能量是非常大的
but so far
可是到目前為止
Humans have not yet been able to take full advantage of
人類還沒有辦法充分地利用
other than using it as a bomb
除了把它拿去做炸彈以外
there seems to be no good way
好像沒有什麼好辦法
take full advantage of
拿來充分地使用
But in the US and in the UK
可是在美國 在英國
There are some cohesive atomic furnaces
都有一些合輪合的原子爐
are doing experimental research
都在做實驗性的研究
hope to find
希望能夠找到
can we replace
是不是我們可以作為取代
Now new personnel come to use
現在新的人員來使用
Except for the case of the sun
太陽除了這樣子的情況以外
It also emits what we call light
它還會放出我們稱作光的
what is light
那什麼是光呢
In fact, from a more scientific point of view,
其實以比較科學的角度去看的話
The stars are actually emitting battery radiation
恆星事實上是放出電池輻射
In fact, it is a dose of radiation
事實上也就是一種輻射的人量
The amount of radiation
這種輻射的人量
what we call light
我們平常稱作光
The reason is because in all its range
原因是因為在它所有的範圍裡頭
quite a while
有相當的一段
We human eyes can see
我們人類的肉眼可以看得到
call it visible light
稱它作可見光
In the shorter wavelength part of visible light
在可見光的波長比較短的部分
and the longer part of the words
和比較長的部分的話
we have some names
大家有些名稱
Some of the names are familiar
生書 有些名稱也很熟悉
For example, the possibility of relative cosmic color lines
譬如說宇宙色線相對的可能生書
Gamma color line because now the brain
Gamma色線因為現在腦部的
If there is a flow knife
如果有流開刀的話
We say Gamma knife refers to Gamma color line
我們說Gamma刀就是指Gamma色線
Then the X-ray is from Professor Wang Yu.
然後X線 什麼王玉教授的
research expertise
研究的專長
Then at the wavelength towards
然後在波長往
words here
在這邊的話
stick to visible light
貼到可見光
The shorter wavelength on the left is ultraviolet light
左邊比較波長短的是紫外線
Infrared rays with longer wavelengths
波長長的話是紅外線
if you go down
再下去的話
microwaves are radio waves
微波很無線電波
It's all familiar to everyone.
通通都是大家比較熟悉的了
In this posture
那在這個姿勢上面來講
We call it photoreplenishment
我們稱它是光補學
this is gossip
這是閒話一句
what does it teach us
它讓我們領悟到什麼呢
we just said
我們剛剛前面說
Scientists must have a special scope
科學家要有特殊的scope
to see special targets
去看特殊的目標
the same reason
同樣的道理
Spectroscopy also allows us to see
光譜學也讓我們看到
We use different wavelengths
我們用不同的波長
Or if you look at it with frequency light
或者說頻率的光去看的話
We can see inside matter
我們可以看到物質裡頭
different phenomena
不同的現象
don't go into detail about what kind of phenomenon
不去細講什麼樣的現象
But these different phenomena
可是這些不同的現象
In fact, it allows us to have new perspectives and perspectives
事實上就讓我們可以有新的視野和動見
say again
表示再次說
Tell us the tool should be right
告訴我們工具要對
And look for the right direction
以及找的方向要對
as if you see
就好像你看
if you want to watch desktop
如果你想看台式的話
I probably wouldn't intentionally switch to a Chinese-style channel.
大概不會故意轉到華式的頻道去
So I just have to see desktops on that channel
所以我就非要在那個頻道上看到台式不可
then we will never see
那我們相對是永遠看不到的
The reason is very simple
這個道理是很簡單的
Another form of energy deserves our attention
另外一種能量的形式值得我們注意的
chemical energy
就是化學能
This is especially true on Earth
這是尤其在地球上
more noticeable energy
更應該注意到的能量
We just said that the interaction of functions
我們剛剛說職能的互動
Most of the aforementioned nuclear energy
前面講的大部分是核能
But when matter is formed
可是物質在形成的時候
often release energy
常常會要釋放出能量
if it is destroyed
如果是在破壞的時候
often absorb energy
常常要吸收能量
In fact, if we put it in more precise terms
其實如果以更精準的話去講
From your chemist's point of view
你化學家的角度去講這句話的話
It should be about atoms bonded together
應該是講結合在一起的原子
if you pull it out
你如果要把它拉開來的話
You have to give it its full amount
你非給它原量不可
If the separated atoms
如果分開來的原子
if you want to tie it together
你要把它連結到一起去的話
it will surely let people out
它一定會放出人量出來
This is from a scientist's point of view
這個是以一個科學家的角度去看
is a rule like this
是這樣子的一個規則
If we use this picture to see
那我們用這個圖去看的話
If this axis is the original quantity
如果這個軸是原量
If this axis is the distance between atoms
這個軸如果是原子間的距離
You will find that when you put two pro-atoms
你就會發現當你把兩個親原子
let it get closer
讓它靠得比較近一點以後
Its original volume is to go to the bottom
它的原量是往低的底下走
and when you go to the lowest place
然後走到最低的地方的時候
Logically, it is the most stable place
照道理就是它最穩定的地方
That is, many middle school students here
也就是很多在座的中學同學
What you learned in middle school or high school failed
你們國中或高中所學的未能
also failed at the lowest time
也是未能在最低的時候
it should be most stable
它應該最穩定
But if you let it get closer
可是你如果讓它再靠近的話
electron and atom box inside it
它裡面的電子和原子盒
there is power
就有相次的力量
so it deliberately pushes them back apart
所以它會故意再把它們擠開
So the number will rise again
所以這個人量又會上升
So probably when stable
所以大概在穩定的時候
it's all within this range
它都在這個範圍之內
So its distance has a stable range
所以它的距離是有一個穩定的範圍的
Of course if you give it energy
那當然你如果給它能量的話
let it climb
讓它爬山
Just like we need energy to climb a mountain
就像我們要爬山需要能量一樣
Let it go when the distance gets farther and farther
讓它到距離越拉越遠的時候
you can take it apart
你就可以把它拆開來了
So chemical energy is what makes matter
所以化學能是使得物質
when forming and breaking
在形成和破壞的時候
The number of people incidental to the change
變化所附帶產生的人量
At this time there will be a
這個時候就會出現一個
Scientists have two perspectives to see things
科學家有兩個角度的觀點去看事情
If you consider matter as the subject
如果你把物質看作主體的話
you will find
你就會發現
The substance is changing its form
這個物質在改變它的形態
For example, the atoms I just mentioned
譬如說我剛說的原子
when combined
結合的時候
or when separated
或者分開的時候
or when new substances are formed
或者形成新的物質的時候
when rearranging
重新排列的時候
it will have to come in or go out with the energy
它就會有隨著能量進來或出去
So as if matter is the subject
所以好像物質是主體
energy is class
能量是課體
energy goes out
能量就進行出出
But you also have another way to see it
可是你也有另外一種方式去看它
regard energy as subject
把能量看作主體
And if we regard the matter as a subject
然後把物質看成是課題的話
When energy changes from high to low in that place
能量在那個地方高高低低改變的時候
Matter follows, so we have to accept a little more energy
物質就跟著 只好要多接受一點能量
If it receives less energy, its shape will change back and forth
少接受一點能量 它的形態就會變來變去
So watch your goals look at energy
所以看你的目標看在能量上面
still look at the material
還是看在物質上面
All in all, a very basic concept
總而言之 一個非常基本的觀念
Not just nuclear energy or chemical energy
不只是不管是核能也好或者化學能也好
its different sizes
它的大小不一樣
But it will be accompanied by changes in matter
可是都會伴隨著物質跟著變化
This is the most important point
這個是最重要的一個觀點
if you don't study science
如果你不是學科學的話
At least you know that energy is always following the change of matter
至少你知道能量永遠跟著物質的變化在進行的
on our planet, especially
在我們的地球上 尤其是
In the top of the air, there are many small molecules
在空氣頂頭的話 有很多小的分子
For example, oxygen is familiar to everyone
譬如說氧氣是大家很熟悉的
That carbon dioxide is what everyone hates
那氧氧化碳是大家很討厭的
Carbon dioxide, everyone is afraid of hearing it now
氧氧化碳 現在大家聽得都怕
then carbon dioxide
然後氧氧化碳
Carbon dioxide is also poisonous
氧氧化碳也是毒氣
But in our body
可是在我們身體裡頭
It is very important for nerve conduction
它卻對神經傳導有很重要的關係
Holiday night can be regarded as
假晚是可以當作
gas to burn
煤氣來燃燒
Peace of mind
安氣
or sulfur dioxide
或者是二氧化硫
So you will find that there are many substances
所以你會發現有很多的物質
Can be spread in our atmospheric city
可以散佈在我們的大氣城裡頭
by us
由我們
increasingly familiar substances
越來越熟悉的物質
I was very familiar with matter when I didn't know science before
和以前不懂科學的時候就很熟悉物質
like this
像這個
it side
它這邊
blue is
藍色的是
Green molecules
青分子
red oxygen molecule
紅色的是氧分子
and after you burn it
然後你把它燃燒了以後
it can combine into water molecules
它就能夠結合變成水分子
So this one that looks like Mickey Mouse's head
所以這個看起來像米老鼠的頭的
with two ears
有兩個耳朵的
water molecules
就是水分子
other small molecules
那其他的一些小分子
I won't go into detail
我就不去細數
but macromolecules
可是大分子的話
like our genetics
譬如說像我們的遺傳
this
這個
genetic code
遺傳密碼的
Responsible DNA
負責的DNA
its atoms
它的原子
The atoms in a molecule are at least
一個分子的原子起碼是
more than a thousand
上千以上
so you can tell
所以你可以看得出來
At least hundreds of thousands of atoms
起碼是幾百上千的原子
is very large
是非常龐大的
so simple
所以簡單
Whether it is a simple molecule or a complex molecule
簡單的分子也好 複雜的分子也好
This is what caused our earth
這個是造成我們地球上
One of the most basic reasons why its landscape is so diverse
它的景觀非常多樣化的一個最基本的原因
So we say that when the sun uses electromagnetic radiation
所以我們說當太陽藉著電磁輻射
It is far from feeling that the energy is sent to the planet
遠遠不覺得把能量送到了行星上面來的時候
The matter on the planet because of the incoming energy
行星上的物質因為進來的能量
it can start to change
它就可以開始發生變化
This is the change between people and matter that I just emphasized again and again
這是我剛一再強調的人和物質之間的變化
Nature begins with nuclear energy and head and chemical energy and head
自然界從核能與頭以及化學能與頭
Transformed its matter and created our world
轉換出了它的物質 也造就了我們這個世界
One of them is that everyone often
其中有一件大家最近常常
Even in recent years, students often hear
就是近年來學生也常常聽到
What you often see in the newspapers is the greenhouse effect
大家報紙上也常常看到的就是溫室效應
The greenhouse effect is what I just said
溫室效應在我剛說了
Often when the media introduces them inaccurately
常常在媒體介紹的時候不準確的情況之下
Now quite a lot of people are scared when they hear about the greenhouse effect
現在已經有蠻多的民眾聽到溫室效應就很害怕
Think that the greenhouse effect after the increase of carbon dioxide
覺得二氧化碳一增加以後溫室效應
will make our temperature higher and higher
就會使得我們的溫度越來越高
Then we just get sadder and sadder
然後我們就直接越來越難過
And it's causing big changes in the climate
而且是造成氣候很大的變化
Count all the burials on it
把所有的葬都算到它頭上去
In fact, the greenhouse effect is harmful to the ability of human beings to live in this world.
其實溫室效應是對人類能夠活在這個世界上
A very important life-saving effect
非常重要的一個救命的效應
Because when the sun shines radiation on the earth,
因為當太陽把輻射人照到地球上面來以後
it will reflect back
它會反射回去
after reflecting back
反射回去以後
There are actually some molecules in the top of the atmosphere here.
這邊大氣層頭其實有一些分子
Putting it in the atmosphere can reflect it back
佈在大氣層頭可以把它再反射回來
So look at the picture below
所以看下面這張圖
It is easier for everyone to understand
大家是更容易了解的
Infrared rays actually affect the greenhouse effect
紅外線事實上是影響溫室效應
The most critical radiation dose
最關鍵的輻射人量
It's because of incoming radiation
它原因是因為照進來的輻射
when reflected
在反射出去的時候
it doesn't all go out
它沒有全部出去
it's blocked by some gas and put back
它被一些氣體擋住放回來
some infrared light here
那這裡頭的一些紅外線
is actually what keeps our planet warm
事實上是使得保持住我們地球的溫度
actually very gentle
其實非常的溫和
Why do we say that the temperature of the earth is very mild?
我們為什麼說地球的溫度很溫和呢
because the surface of the sun
因為太陽的地表
should not say it is the surface
不應該說它是地表
this calendar
這個日表
It should be 6000 degrees C
應該是說6000度C
Yes, if we want to encounter such an environment
是我們如果要碰到這樣的環境的話
we say dire straits
我們說水深火熱
Probably our whole body is gasified
大概我們整個身體通通都氣化
impossible
不可能存在的
If you go to read history
你如果是去讀一下歷史
When Pompeii was covered by volcanoes
龐貝城被火山蓋住的時候
When its hot air sweeps over people
它那個熱氣掃到人身上的時候
less than 6000 degrees
還不到6000度
The temperature of thousands of degrees is already
幾千度的溫度就已經是
Everyone gasified and exploded.
所有的人通通都氣化爆炸掉了
But if it's in the desert
可是如果是在沙漠區的話
The temperature is relatively high
溫度其實相對也高
It may be higher than 40 degrees
就是有可能高於40度
words from the rainforest
熱帶雨林的話
Similar to today's Taipei
跟今天台北差不多
35 degrees C
35度C
If Antarctica
如果是南極的話
The average temperature can be maintained below zero
平均溫度可以到維持在零下
The words of the ocean are in fact the hub of regulation
海洋的話事實上是調節的樞紐
the average temperature on Earth
使得地球上的平均溫度
Should be around 15 degrees C
應該在差不多15度C
lowest words
最低的話
It's hard to get below -50 degrees C on earth
地球上很難低過-50度C
It's hard to be higher than 10 degrees C at noon
最高的話很難高過正午10度C
So it is relative to the scale of facilities
所以它相對以設施的尺度來講
100 degrees C is not a very wide range
100度C不是一個非常寬的範圍
It's not like we don't talk about Mars today
不像是我們今天不講火星
On Mars, 200 degrees C at night
火星的話晚上200度C
It gets up to 400 degrees C during the day
白天升到400度C
This change is hundreds of degrees C
這個變化的話好幾百度C
so the difference can be huge
所以差別可以很大
In addition to the atmosphere
除了大氣以外
Other aspects of the crust can pay a little attention
其他的地殼方面可以稍微注意一下
I can actually speed up this part a bit.
這一部分我其實可以加快一點
You will find that our earth is not a uniform sphere
你會發現我們的地球不是一個均勻的球體
It has a core and a core that we call geochill
它有核心也有一個我們稱作地寒的
In fact, what we are most familiar with is actually the surface of the earth.
事實上我們最熟悉的其實是地表
the part called the crust
就是稱作地殼的部分
because it is a hard shape
因為是一個硬的形形
Hard shape means we stand on it
硬的形形意思就是我們站在它上面的話
it is hard
它是硬的
not like jupiter
不像是像木星
We have four hard shapes which are Mercury, Venus, Mars and Earth
我們有四個硬的形形是水星、金星、火星和地球
These four are hard shapes
這四個是硬的形形
But others such as Jupiter
可是其他的譬如說木星
Purus Uranus Neptune
普星 天王星 海王星
are gaseous planets
都是比較氣態的行星
For a hard cross planet like this
像這種比較硬的十字行星的話
in terms of its entire structure
它的整個的構造來講的話
Earth Chill and Earth and Yes are in it
地寒和地和是在裡面
It is obvious that the middle longitudinal density is high
很明顯中間縱密度高
It's a little less dense here
這邊密度再小一點
outermost minimum
最外面最小
Indicates that chemistry has a
表示化學有一種
Chemical consonance means according to density
化學靈犀的意思就是按照密度
Sink vertically Float upward gently
縱的往下沉 輕的往上飄
That's what I mean
就是這個意思
So roughly speaking
所以大致來講
The lightest density is probably outside the crust
密度最輕的大概都在地殼外面
But in the part where the ground is cold
可是在地寒的部分的話
it actually has some heat
它其實有一些熱
let out the heat
放出來這些熱
is to make it convective
是使得它產生對流現象
convection phenomenon that is
對流現象也就是說
hot part
熱的部分
its density will be lower
它密度就會向低
just run up
就往上跑
Just like our air
就跟我們的空氣一樣的道理
so don't look
所以你不要看
Are you saying that this is not the lithosphere of soil rocks?
你說這都不是都是土壤岩石的岩石圈嗎
it can still flow
它照樣可以流動
slow flow
緩慢的流動
So there is convection
所以產生對流現象
so when
所以當
words at the core
在核心的部分的話
It has no effect on the surface temperature
它對於地表的溫度是沒有影響的
But for the convective part of the cold
可是對於地寒的對流的部分
it may have an effect
卻是可能有影響
especially if there is gas in it
尤其裡面有氣體
a class of explosive words
一具類的爆炸的話
It might have erupted from a volcano.
就可能從火山噴出來了
let's jump over
我們這個跳過去
So volcanoes are relative to the surface
所以火山對於地表來講
is a very important thing
是很重要的一件事情
We often say that the surface of the earth
我們常常說地球表面
is a living form
是一個活的形形
One of the very important reasons
其中很重要的一個原因
That is, we now have active volcanoes for everyone
就是我們現在人人有活的火山
Still working on the surface
在地表上還在運作
Datun Mountain is a repair volcano
大屯山的話是一個修火山
On the face of it
目前表面上來看
no very clear apparent activity
沒有非常清楚的明顯的活性
But in fact judging from its flow prevention pit
可是事實上以它的流防坑來看
still working
還是在運作的
Maybe hundreds of years or a thousand years from now
也許幾百年以後或一千年以後
It might explode again
它還會再爆炸也不一定
But in the Atlantic
不過在大西洋
we can see an obvious
我們就可以看到一個很明顯的
from the cold
從地寒
all the way to the surface
一直到地表
it's because of the persistent heat
它因為持續的熱
Convection like this is maintained
維持了這樣子的對流現象
Then the gas comes out
然後氣體噴出來
so that the bottom of the Atlantic Ocean
就使得大西洋的海底
Expand to both sides
往兩面擴張
so it has an atlantic level ditch
所以它有一個大西洋級的溝
still going on
一直持續的還在
broadened process development
擴寬的過程發展
still under development
還在發展之中
So this magma its movement
所以這個岩漿它的運動
Earth's surface provided
提供的地球表面
very important vitality
非常重要的活力
We even say it is the vitality of construction
我們甚至於說它是建造的活力
for example
譬如說
Look carefully at the words of the Atlantic class
仔細去看大西洋級的話
it comes out warm sea water
它這個出來溫暖的海水
around this
在這個周圍
We used to think that in this hotter seawater
我們以前認為這個比較熱的海水裡面
no living things
不可能有生物
now we find
現在我們發現
In fact, at such a high temperature
其實在這麼高的溫度情況之下
There are still very special creatures
還是有很特殊的生物
And it has good nutrients to grow
而且有蠻好的養分可以滋長
So don't read that in this
所以不要看說在這個
at such a high temperature
這麼高的溫度情況之下
It is not easy to say that biological survival
說生物生存是很不容易的
In fact, organisms are very easy to adapt to the environment
事實上生物是很容易適應環境的
So we have a saying here
所以我們這邊有一句話說
The earth is like Athena in Greek mythology
地球就像希臘神話很頭的雅典納一樣
It has both properties
它同時具備兩種性質
It seems to have the wisdom of all things
它好像又具有資深萬物的智慧
But on the other hand it also has a lot of violence
可是另一方面它也具有很大的暴力
You sometimes see disasters happening on Earth
大家有些時候看到地球的災難在發生的時候
key report
又提到關鍵報告
The key report is that
關鍵報告就是說
It's not that aliens are coming, it's that
不是外星人來了就是說
Then there is something special
然後就是有什麼特殊的現象
For example, Mr. Wang is going to run away somewhere to hide.
譬如說王老師就要逃到什麼地方去躲一躲這種的
From the point of view of scientists
以科學家來看
nature is not particularly kind
大自然並不是特別仁慈
But it doesn't have to be particularly cruel
可是它也未必特別的殘酷
most likely it manifests
很可能它表現出來的
sometimes we feel indifferent
我們有時候是覺得冷漠
when its violence chokes some life
當它的暴力凝倒某些生命的時候
we sometimes think it's cold
我們有時候覺得它是冷酷的
But when it is experienced in all things
可是它資深萬物的時候
We think it's actually full of cancer
我們覺得它其實是充滿癡癌
That's why the Greeks called it Mother Earth
這也是為什麼希臘人稱它為大地之母
In the process of the development of the earth I just said that we have
在地球發展的過程之中我剛剛說我們已經
about 4.6 billion years ago
大約有差不多46億年的時間了
The scale actually makes it very wide
這個尺度事實上把它放得非常的寬
If it's 4.6 billion years here
如果這邊是46億年的話
That's 4 billion years
這就是40億年
So here it is 2.1 billion years
所以這邊是21億年
1.1 billion years here
這邊是11億年
500 million years here
這邊是5億年
If we look a little closer
如果我們稍微仔細點點去看的話
earliest stone found
最早的石頭發現的
approximately over 4 billion years
大約是在超過40億年的時間
is a stone found in Australia
是在澳洲所發現的一塊石頭
you will find
你會發現
1984 is very close to now
1984年距離現在時間非常的近
But about 30 years
不過30年的時間差不多
ingredients in it
它裡面的成分
In fact, using the current single catty analysis
事實上用現在單斤解析
can already be seen
都已經可以看得出來
you can clearly see
你可以很清楚的看到
It has two metal atoms in it
它裡面有兩種金屬原子
one is high
一種是高
one is young
一種是幼
In other words, of course, there are sheep
其他的話當然還有羊
So we already know the ingredients
所以成分我們都已經知道了
stone like this
像這樣子的石頭
it's actually igneous rock
它其實是火塵岩
was produced at a very early age
是在非常早的時代就產生的
except this
除了這個以外
there are still some very old rocks on earth
地球上還有一些很老的石頭
For example, it was discovered in Canada in the 1940s
譬如說在加拿大1940期就發現了
It is in fact in Greenland, Iceland, probably
它事實上在冰島格林蘭大概都
Earlier rocks were found in that area
那一區都發現了有比較早一點的岩石
Also some bacteria
另外還有一些細菌
Of course, this bacterium is no longer a living bacterium.
這個細菌當然它已經不是活的細菌了
actually a fossil
事實上是化石
So judging by its size
所以以它的這個尺寸來看的話
Very likely a fossil of bacteria
非常可能是細菌的化石
Its size is actually only 10 to 20
它的大小事實上只有10到20個
We can only do micron
我們只能做微米
That's 10 belly fat
也就是10的腹六脂肪
It was discovered more than 30 years ago
它發現的時間距離現在已經有30多一年的時間
In other words, the earliest life on earth
換句話說地球上最早的生命
Probably more than 30 years from now
很可能距離現在有30多一年
the length of time
這個時間的長度
I have a lot of this time scale today
我今天有很多的這個時間的尺度
tell everyone
告訴大家
I am slowly
我自己是在慢慢
accumulated from reading different books
讀不同的書累積起來的
So now I'm getting more and more familiar with this time scale.
所以現在越來越熟悉這個時間的尺度了
if you don't often hear
如果你不常聽的話
Maybe it will be a little uncomfortable for a while
可能一下子會有一點不習慣
35 years is very long
35一年是非常長的
Are some people not even 35 yet?
有些人連35歲都還沒到嘛
Is it right
對嗎
If it's bacteria, let it
那如果是細菌要讓它
It should mean that the cell wants it to
應該是說細胞要讓它
It is more special if it contains the nucleus
比較特別一點有含到細胞核的話
In fact, it's been almost a billion years.
事實上也已經有差不多十幾億年的時間了
We are about 12 years old
我們大概12一年是說
The present plant with a nucleus
現在的這個有細胞核的植物
It's almost 12 years now
現在就是差不多12一年的時間
A very important thing happened in the middle
這個中間發生過一件非常重要的事情
That is, when it is almost 21 years away
也就是差不多距離21年的附近的時候
Oxygen begins to be produced in large quantities on Earth
氧氣開始在地球上大量的產生
Indicates that the earth was in the early days
表示說地球在早期的時候
without as much oxygen as we have now
沒有像我們現在這麼多的氧
So if there are other bacteria present at that time
所以那個時候如果有其他的細菌存在的話
It doesn't live on oxygen
它不是靠著氧氣在過日子的
eukaryotic cells for more than ten years
真核的細胞十幾年
really more like
真正比較像
We look more like animals
我們看起來比較像動物的情況出現
It's been around 500 million years
已經到了差不多五億年附近
Many people, especially children, know
大家很多人尤其小孩子知道
Reptiles were around 200 million years ago
爬蟲類是在兩億年
Just climbed from Mercury Head to the road
才從水銀頭爬到路上去
Because when reptiles appear
因為爬蟲類出現的時候
Dinosaurs also appeared
恐龍也就出現了
So we look at it through the eyes of a chemist
所以我們從化學家的眼光流去看
The most important life is to be able to survive
最重要的生命要能夠維持生存
That is to say, energy must come into it from the outside world.
也就是要有能量從外界進到它的裡面去
It is likely to flow into its body in the form of matter
很可能是以物質的形式進到它的身體流去的
But when you go in, you have to generate energy
可是進去的時候必須產生能量
make it work with energy
讓它裡面有能量的運作
this is any kind of life
這是任何一種生命
no matter what form it is
不管它是什麼樣的形態
We are also good
我們人也好
or the smallest cell
或者最小的細胞也好
or bacteria
或者細菌也好
should have such conditions
都應該要有這樣子的條件
We just talked about the time from 21 to 31 years
我們剛剛講到21年到31年時間的時候
In fact, some photosynthetic life has appeared
其實已經有一些光合作用的生命出現了
In fact, you can now see blue-green algae
事實上你現在可以看到藍綠藻
Also it forms such cells
也它所形成的這樣的細胞
In fact the first thing you see
事實上是最早你看到
is green
是綠色的
Everyone knows that green is because of the leaves of green trees.
綠色大家都知道是因為葉綠樹的緣故
This picture is actually a chemist who wants to spend
這一張的圖其實是一個化學家要花
A picture that took a long time to understand
很長的一段時間才能夠弄懂的一張圖
There are still many things in it that we can't understand
裡面也還有東西很多東西我們不能夠弄懂
But at least everyone learned it in middle school
不過至少大家在念中學的時候都學掉
If you take water and crocodile carbon as raw materials
你如果把水和鱷氧化碳當作原料
put the cells in the leaves to lead
放到葉子的細胞領頭去
Relying on chlorophyll plus light, it is called photosynthesis
靠著葉綠樹加上光所以稱作光和作用
it produces oxygen and glucose
它可以產生氧氣和葡萄糖
Symptoms actually have a very complicated operation of the number of people
症頭其實有非常複雜的人量的運作
And the operation of this human quantity it goes from plant to animal
而這個人量的運作它從植物到動物身上
have a similar mechanism at work
都有類似的機制在運作
Our so-called ADP ATP is actually called
我們這邊所謂的ADP ATP事實上叫做
Dilingic acid is a kind of plum is a kind of enzyme
二靈酸是一種是一種是一種梅類是一種酵素
ATP is Mitsubishi acid
ATP的話是三菱酸
Alteration of trees by rhombic acid
靠著菱酸的樹木的改變
After making its chemical reaction happen
使得它的化學反應發生以後
There are changes in energy
有能量的變化
At the same time, if there is another breathing effect here
那同時在這邊另外呼吸作用的話
Of course our bodies rely on oxygen to burn
當然我們身體頭要靠著氧氣來燃燒
Provide energy for the functioning of our body
提供我們身體的運作的能量
So glucose can be used as fuel here
所以葡萄糖就可以在這邊當作燃料
So the two big cycles are chemically
所以兩個大的循環在化學來講
is very important
是非常重要的
Using chemistry to exchange between matter and energy
在物質和能量之間用化學人在交換
make our lives work
使得我們生命可以運作
this is a very important thing
這是非常重要一件事情
But if we look at it from a historical perspective
可是我們從一個歷史的角度來看的話
We were just talking about half a billion years ago
我們剛剛談到五億年附近的時候
In fact, there are a lot of special creatures appearing
其實是有非常多的特殊的生物出現
Let's see the next one will be more clear
我們看下面一張會更清楚
This time is about 500 million years
這個時間差不多五億年
It's called Han Wuji
是叫做韓五季
If you go to the Canadian Rockies
你如果到加拿大的洛基山脈
look up
上面去看
Or if you go to see it in China's Yunnan and Guangxi areas
或者是中國的雲南廣西一帶去看的話
You can find words like this
都可以找到這樣子的話
It can be seen as an animal
它一看就知道是動物
Because it's not like a lobster, it's like a cockroach
因為不像龍蝦就像蟑螂
But now on earth
不過現在在地球上
you can't find it anywhere
你通通都找不到它了
because almost the vast majority of
因為幾乎絕大部分
They're all extinct
通通都已經滅種了
it's almost in han wu ji
它差不多在韓武紀
That is, 500 million years from now
也就是距現在五億年的時候
It's all of a sudden gone extinct
它突然之間通通的滅絕掉
after extinction
滅絕掉以後
Many fossils are left in the marble
很多的化石就留在大理石的
inside the rock formation
岩層裡頭
So when I just said that in Luojishan and
所以在我剛說在加拿大的落雞山和
Southern part of mainland China
大陸的中國大陸的南部
can see
都可以看得到
But you now because it is a hard-shelled animal
可是你現在因為它是硬殼類的動物
So after you dug it out
所以你挖出來了以後
You find that its shape is still in that place
你發現它的形狀都還留在那個地方
But when these creatures suddenly a large number
可是當這些生物突然大量的
dead when extinct
死掉 絕種的時候
there is a very interesting thing
有一個很有趣的事情
between 500 million and 200 million years
就在五億到兩億年之中間
there are very fast
有非常快速的
Haiying head creatures are also good
海盈頭生物也好
and creatures that walk on the ground
以及走到地面上的生物也好
rapid development
迅速的發展
What does this mean?
這表示一個什麼事情呢
when the environment is right
當環境合適的時候
some creatures are lost
有一些生物喪失了
its chance of survival
它生存的機會
Other creatures suddenly
另外一些生物就突然之間
get its chance of survival
獲得它的生存的機會
In other words, what we now call the exchange of ecological blocks
換句話說就是我們現在所謂的生態區塊的交換
Because if you give up your position
因為你如果把位置讓出來的話
Then I'll sit down so the wind blows
那我就坐下去 所以大風吹
So the earth is actually doing destructive creation again and again
所以地球其實是一再的在做破壞性的創造
Just like the volcano I just mentioned
就剛剛我剛剛講的火山一樣的道理
natural disasters on our earth
天然的災害在我們地球上
It's been decades
已經是幾十一年的時間
never disappeared
從來沒有消失過
we can talk so much today
我們今天能口這麼多的
like taiwan
就像台灣
Every year when a typhoon comes, we will be nervous
每一年颱風來我們都會緊張
Because of landslides, right?
因為有土石流 對不對
Every time an earthquake comes, we will be nervous
每一次的地震來我們都會緊張
don't know how much it will be
不知道它會是幾幾的
Even recently, everyone is a little worried about the tsunami
甚至於最近大家對海嘯都還有點擔心
If you take the 46-year time scale of the entire earth
你如果把整個地球的46年時間尺度
put it to the end of the day
放到一天頭去
This is what many people can see in books
這是很多人在書上可以看到的
In this way to describe the history of our earth
用這樣的方式去描述我們地球的歷史
it has a total of 24 hours
它總共有24小時
In these 24 hours you
在這24小時你
Really, when we just said that bacteria capable of photosynthesis appeared
真正我們剛說能夠行光合作用的細菌出現的時候
It's almost morning
其實已經差不多到早上了
That is to say, after 9 o'clock
也就是說9點多的時候
Because it's 12 o'clock, so around 9 o'clock
因為12點 所以大概9點多的時候
it just appeared
它才出現
before dawn
天還沒有亮的時候
what we can see
我們所能夠看到的
In fact, it's just the germ of life
事實上只是生命的萌芽而已
Sunshine bacteria only appear after dawn
真正天亮了以後光陽細菌才出現
The emergence of blue-green algae has reached noon
藍綠藻的出現已經到了中午了
We just said that after the emergence of nucleated dimensional organisms
我們剛說增核的維生物出現以後
Only then will there be real plants appearing behind
才會引到後面有真正的植物出現
You see, the nucleated dimensional organisms are about a billion years old as we just said
你看增核的維生物差不多我們剛說十幾億年
so it's already afternoon
所以已經是下午的時間了
then it was early
然後還早出現
I just said that there is an animal without vertebrae in Hanwuji
剛說這個寒五季的有顆無積椎的動物
In fact, it was almost 9:10 at night.
事實上已經到了晚上差不多9點10點的時候
when plants appear
植物出現的時候
It's actually been almost 11 years since now
事實上已經距離現在差不多11年
last less than an hour
最後不到一個小時
Turret just showed up
Turret才出現
and then in the last three minutes
然後在最後三分鐘的時候
not our kind
還不是我們這種人類
If humans related to us appear
是跟我們有關係的人類出現的話
Just like Sun Wukong came out of "Huaguo Mountain"
就像孫悟空從《花果山》出來一樣
Three minutes to make a fuss in the sky
三分鐘的時間大鬧天空
The earth is messed up
地球就搞得一塌糊塗
So if you look at it over such a long time
所以如果你從這麼長的時間來看的話
If you take a look at this National Geographic magazine,
你們如果稍微去看一下這個國家地理雜誌說
Sharks may have lived on Earth for the last year
鯊魚可能在地球上已經存活了上一年的時間
Is it right
對嗎
So how expensive is the long life
所以活得久的才是多貴
I often say this to my wife
我常常跟我太太講這句話
Is it right
對嗎
Then nature has a very long time
然後大自然非常漫長的時間裡頭
I think time is one of its deepest wisdoms
我認為時間就是它一個最深層的智慧
In other words, on Earth, if there is no time-tested
換句話說在地球上如果沒有經過時間考驗的
even if there is life to speak
即使是有生命來講的話
It often skims like we say
它常常匆匆的一撇像我們說的
Floating for admissions purposes
浮游招生而目的
In fact, from the point of view of life
其實是在生命的角度來看的話
we can't say it doesn't make sense
我們不能說它沒有意義
But if it is better
可是它如果講得好一點
It's like knowing, like a shooting star
它就是像會心 像流星一樣
Of course humans come into this world
當然人類走到這個世界上
You can see there is a long record
你可以看有很長的紀錄
If there are at least two species of hominids
人科出現的話 至少有兩種
One is not the number of people but the number of ancient people, the other is the number of people
一種不是人數而是古人數 一種是人數
We will compare the number of people as a closer relationship with us
我們會比較把人數看成跟我們關係比較近
In fact, about 5 million years from now to
事實上大概是距離現在500萬年到
7 million years is the latest data
700萬年時間是目前最新的數據
Maybe it will change, not necessarily
說不定還會改變也不一定
Is considered to be the first to break away from the black star
是認為最早脫離黑星星
started to go in the direction of our humans
開始往我們人類的方向走的
The earliest group, but it still belongs to ancient humans
最早的一群 可是它仍然屬於古人類的
when the number of people
走到人數的時候
The first type is probably Renren or Qiaoren
第一種大概是人人或者稱作巧人
There are two names to translate it
有兩種名稱去翻譯它
Hablas is translated as a capable person by someone, and a clever person by someone else
Hablas有人翻作能人 有人翻作巧人
The reason is because they can make tools
原因是因為他們可以製造工具
But from the perspective of the ancient Yuan
可是以古元屬來看的話
They already walk on two feet
他們已經用兩隻腳走路了
It's just that their size, height, in all respects
只不過他們的大小 高度 各方面來講
Looks like a chimpanzee
跟黑猩猩還滿像的
But chimpanzees, beware
可是黑猩猩你要注意
It walks on four legs most of the time
它大部分時間是用四隻腳走路
It must have four legs when it runs
它跑的時候一定有四隻腳
Occasionally stand up like us
偶然有時候學我們一樣站起來一下
So from this point of view
所以以從這個地方來看的話
In fact, from the earliest possible
我們事實上從最早的大概
This place is almost 2 million years old
這個地方差不多200萬年
Then into Africa's Homo erectus
然後進到非洲的直立人
Then to Homo erectus in Asia
然後到亞洲的直立人
This place is almost 800,000 years old
這個地方是差不多80萬年
If we say that the 600,000 to 800,000 people in Beijing
我們如果說北京人的60萬到80萬
almost here
就差不多在這個地方
So the tree goes from like this
所以這個樹從這樣子走
You can watch our intelligence in this place
你可以看我們的智能在這個地方
so this is like
所以這個像
How do you say it's like a maze
怎麼講 迷宮一樣
Go to this place and turn again
走到這個地方要再轉
go here to be able to
轉到這邊才能夠
I can't get over here
這邊就過不來了
In fact from this
事實上是從這一條
To be able to transfer to our intelligence
才能夠轉到我們智能這邊來
Our nearest neighbors are supposed to be the Leandertas.
據理我們最近的是里安德塔人
A while ago in Indonesia found a
在前一陣子印尼發現了一個
They're about 20,000 away from our time
他們距離我們時間差不多是兩萬
20,000 years is very close
兩萬年是非常近的
But another one came out
可是是另外一隻出來的
Most anthropologists currently believe that
目前大部分人類學家認為
Not from the same one
不是同一隻出來的
So it's from this one
所以是從這一隻出來的
But this is still speculation
不過這個目前大家還在猜測
We are not chief anthropologists
我們不是主要的人類學家
but at least we know
可是至少我們知道
in over a million years
在一百多萬年
around 1.5 million years ago
大約一百五十萬年附近的時候
Why do we call him material civilization
我們為什麼稱他說是物質文明的
before dawn
黎明之前呢
because of the time they were created
因為他們所創造出來的時期
is very clear to see
是很清楚的看到
with what we call the hands of others
有我們所謂的將人之手
Traces of operation knocked out
操作的痕跡敲打出來的
Obviously a stone knife like this
很明顯像這樣子的石刀
It can already be used to cut tougher
已經可以用來切割比較有韌性的
For example, thin skin presses and things like that
譬如說瘦皮壓這類的東西
So it's everyone or a coincidence
所以這是人人或者巧人
time from now
距離現在的時間
from about 1.5 million years ago
從差不多一百五十萬年
over a period of more than two million years
到超過兩百萬年的這段時間裡頭
That
那
It is very important, a kind of personnel that can be used by creatures like humans
很重要一種屬於人這樣子的生物會用的人員
We can also say tool
我們可以說也是工具
The earliest we know we will use is the Beijinger
最早我們知道會用的就是北京人
Because there are many places in their holes that have been burned
因為在他們的洞頭發現有很多地方是用火燒過的
When we were studying in the early days, it was said that it was about 500,000 years away from now
早期我們念書的時候說是差不多距離現在50萬年
Judging from the current data, it must be at least 600,000 to 800,000 years old
以現在資料來看的話 起碼要在60萬到80萬年
But when I was studying, many people thought
不過我念書的時候很多人認為
Beijingers should be Chinese or Chinese
北京人就應該是現在中國人的或者華人
In particular, the two watersheds should not be the ancestors of the Huangke watershed.
尤其是兩顆流域 也不應該是黃殼流域的祖先
From the perspective of today's anthropologists, this should not be the case
以今天人類學家來看應該不是如此
The vast majority of anthropologists in our world today would believe that
今天我們全世界的人類絕大部分的人類學家會相信
We flew from the east after several migrations
我們是經過好幾次的遷徙從東飛出來的
not from mainland China
而不是從中國大陸出來的
fire is very important
用火非常的重要
Because if we use fire, it will probably make us cross the glacier.
因為用火的話很可能會使得我們度過冰河事情
Learn a little about the Ice Age
稍微了解一下冰河時期
so important to us
對我們太重要了
if you know the history
你如果知道這些歷史的話
just know why a scientist
就知道為什麼一個科學家
while looking at things
在看事情的時候
Although we are concerned about our future
我們雖然對我們的未來
Sometimes very cautious and nervous
有的時候很謹慎 很緊張
But we won't be easily afraid
可是我們不會輕易的害怕
The longest glacier on earth
目前地球上最長的一條冰河
is in the alps
是在阿爾卑斯山上
In fact, it's been a long time since what I just said
其實事實上距離我剛剛說很遠的時間
2.5 billion years 2.1 billion years
25億年 21億年
200 million years by 41 years
到41年 2億年
Evidence of glaciers everywhere
通通都有冰河的證據
But within a million years
可是100萬年內
at least 8 times
起碼有8次
we watch the record
我們看紀錄
This record in the last 1 million years
這種紀錄在最近的100萬年
1 million years and 4 billion years
100萬年跟40幾億年
that time is very short
那個時間是很短的
Now scientists only need to go to Greenland
現在的科學家只要到格林蘭
or the North Pole
或者是北極的地方
find a way to put
想辦法把
make a hole
打一個洞
beat into the ice
打到冰心裡面去
Also because it has a welling hole layer
也就因為它有湧洞層
The ice core can be beaten for several kilometers
打下去的冰心可以打好幾公里
The ice brought up can be analyzed for the
拿上來的冰可以分析裡面的
dull atmosphere
大氣沉悶
you can know that time
就可以知道那個時候
Atmosphere Water Content Temperature 1 Million Years Ago
一百萬年前的大氣 含水量 溫度
All kinds of information can be obtained
各方面的資訊都可以拿得到
So let's look at the above symbols to see
所以我們看這個上面的符號來看
one two three four five six seven eight
一二三四五六七八
it has eight stages written on it
它上面寫了八個階段
But I am a little curious why there are two
可是我有一點好奇為什麼這邊是兩個
Then why didn’t it write this? I don’t quite understand it.
那這個它為什麼沒有寫 這個我有點不太懂
But let's take a look at this picture
不過我們稍微看一下這個圖
Here is the current average temperature
這邊是目前平均的溫度
This is where there is more ice
這邊是冰比較多的地方
Here is a place with less ice
這邊是冰比較少的地方
So if you go this way, it means the ice age
所以你往這頭走的話表示是冰和時期
If you go this way, it means that the temperature is rising
你如果往這頭走的話表示是溫度升高
So this place is closest to us in this ice and period
所以這個地方距離我們最近的這個冰和時期
About 15,000 to 30,000 years
差不多一萬五千年到三萬年
still a long time, right?
還是很長的時間對不對
Because 15,000 years seems very far away from us
因為一萬五千年距離我們來講好像很遙遠
But it is already the closest ice age to us
可是已經是距離我們最近的一個冰和時期
The one farther away from us in a million years
在一百萬年以後距離我們比較遠的這個
Like this seven million to here
像這個七百萬到這邊的話
There should be an ice age of 7.5 million
應該大七百五十萬是有一個冰和時期的
Then around 600,000 years ago
然後才差不多60萬年附近的時候
So we just said the era of Beijingers
所以我們剛剛說北京人的時代
such a big ice age
這麼大的冰河時期
You see it's a million years old
你看它已經是100萬年頭
The record ice chess looks the coldest
紀錄冰棋最看起來最冷的
The stage where the temperature drops the most
溫度下降最多的這個階段
So if you don't know how to use fire like them
所以像他們那樣如果不會用火的話
even with fire
即使會用火
To survive such a long ice age
要度過這樣子這麼長的冰河時期
within 100,000 years
10萬年內
You see, this period of time is 100,000 years
你看這段時間有10萬年
Not 100,000 years, at least 50,000 years
沒有10萬年 起碼有5萬年
can you make it through
能夠熬得過去嗎
i think it's not that easy
我想不是那麼容易
Our most recent one lasted almost 15,000 years
我們最近的這次熬了差不多15000年
It's been a rare time
已經是很難得的一段時間
survive this period of time
熬過這一段時間
The rest of the time you see on average every about 100,000 years
其他的時間你看平均每大約10萬年
Just a very big ice age
就一個非常大的冰河時期
So everyone's been talking
所以大家現在一直在講
There are also people who are arguing
也有人在吵說
Maybe a new ice age is coming
說不定新的冰河時期要來了
But before the ice age came
可是冰河時期在還沒有要來之前
We're Already Worrying About Our CO2
我們已經開始擔心我們的二氧化碳
will make us very short time
會使得我們非常短的時間
The temperature drops further
溫度再往下衝
If you go further down, you will break through
再往下衝的話就會突破
The point where the temperature rises the most
溫度上升最高的那個點
So in this potential lens
所以在這個勢鏡頭
is something we're very worried about is going to happen
是我們非常擔心會發生的事情
But what does human beings have to do with this environment?
可是人類跟這個環境有什麼關係呢
pay attention
你稍微注意一下
This is the brain of the black star
這個是黑星星的大腦
Baby time and adult time
Baby的時候和成人的時候
When we don't look at Baby
我們就不看Baby的時候
look over here
就看這邊
as an adult
成人的時候
The black star is about 390 cubic centimeters
黑星星差不多390立方公分
Then came the words of everyone
然後到了人人的話
Almost to close to 500 cm
差不多到了接近500公分
cubic centimeter
立方公分
we human beings are
我們現在人類是
CC over 1300
超過1300的CC
So big at least here
所以大了起碼這邊
more than 4 times
超過了4倍以上
with this
跟這個的話
more than 3 times worse
差到3倍以上
you will find
你會發現
when this baby
這個Baby的時候
If it is compared to the pelvis of the parent star
它跟母星星的骨盆來比角的話
very small
非常的小
So you probably rarely see
所以你大概很難得看到
When the little black star was born
小的黑星星生出來的時候
is dystocia
是難產的
Almost all natural births
幾乎大概都是順產
came out with one sound
一聲就出來了
But if people are going to be born now
可是如果說是現在的人要生出來的話
If he wants to come out directly
他如果直接要出來
you will find the mother's pelvis
你會發現母親的骨盆
The horizontal direction is wider
橫的方向比較寬
The heavier direction is narrower
重的方向比較窄
If you're going to use directions like this
如果你要用這樣子的方向
If you squeeze it out like this
硬從這樣子擠出來的話
very difficult
非常的困難
So when a child is born
所以小孩子生出來的時候
After the miserable
經過慘道
Turn your head 90 degrees
頭要轉一個90度
just came out
才出來
otherwise
要不然的話
It is very easy to have dystocia
非常容易發生難產的事情
So chimpanzees to modern humans
所以黑猩猩到現代人
this brain
這個大腦
has changed a lot
有了非常大的變化
This change doesn't look like it's going to do us any good
這個變化看起來對我們沒什麼好處
because of dystocia
因為造成難產
so
所以
What is the human brain like?
人到底這樣子的大腦
What effect did it have on us
對我們造成了什麼樣的效果
take a look
你們稍微看一下
we call hominid
我們稱作人屬
Said that it's not that we only have human beings now
表示說不是我們現在只有人類
but roughly very close
不過大致非常接近的
Modern humans are within the genus Homo
現代人類是人屬裡頭的
one of them is
其中的一隻就是
Let's see what characteristics he has
我們看看他有什麼特點
Let's just skip the previous paragraph
我們就跳過前面這一段
He said that the size of old growth is necessary to grow
他說了老成長的大小是非要的成長
Then our growth curve is weird
然後我們生長曲線很奇怪
where is the strangeness
奇怪在哪裡呢
the time our infancy comes out
我們的嬰兒期出來的時間
Barely survived when born
剛生出來的時候幾乎活不下去
If you take a scumbag out and leave it in the wild
你如果把一個卑鄙一生出來就丟在野外的話
it must not survive
它一定活不下去
Chimpanzees have a chance
黑猩猩的話還有機會可能
not ideal
也不是很理想
But when we look at Bambi's words
可是我們看小路班比的話
It takes about 5 minutes after birth, and it can stand up after 10 minutes
它大概生出來5分鐘 10分鐘以後就可以站起來
You can run with your mother
跟著母親就可以跑了
So the number of biological words
所以人數的生物的話
Probably need the mother to take care of it when it is born
大概在生出來的時候都需要母親去照顧
This is the characteristic of general martial arts
這是普武類的特徵
Then our childhood was very long
然後我們的童年特別長
Usually 15 years or older to become an adult
通常要15歲以上才會成年
Because this time will be extended
因為這個時間要加長
Our social structure has also changed
我們的社會結構也跟著改變
so all the numbers
所以所有的人數
usually a matriarchal society
通常都是一個母性社會
or magnetic society
或磁性的社會
It is usually several magnetic entities
它通常都是好幾個磁性的個體
at the same time
同時
Take care of one or several babies
照顧一個或幾個的baby
For example, mother and mother's sister
譬如說是母親和母親的姐妹
and take care of her own daughter
和至於她自己的女兒一起照顧
So we can imagine
所以我們可以想像
Why our current monogamy
為什麼我們現在的一夫一妻制
then not
然後又不是
If you are monogamous and have to take care of children
自己一夫一妻要照顧小孩的話
especially took care of two three four
尤其照顧了兩個 三個 四個
even if one
一個的話也就算
if in taiwan
如果在台灣的話
It's just that there are many parents helping
就是有很多的爸媽在幫忙嘛
otherwise why say
要不然為什麼說
It's really hard when you have to take care of children.
這個真的要照顧小孩的時候那麼辛苦
You can see this social structure
你可以看到這個社會結構
It is indeed an opportunity for women to take care of children
的確是女性照顧小孩的機會
still more
還是比較多的
That's because our tool increases meat wetness enhancement
那因為我們的工具增加肉濕性增強
So the body can become healthier
所以身體可以變得比較健康
Then we will have more adaptable athletic ability
然後我們會有比較能夠適應的運動能力
I think this ability
這個能力我是覺得
Especially in modern times it is called extreme sports, right?
尤其在近代的叫做極限運動是嗎
after being invented
被發明出來了以後
It's really hot
真是燙為關子
human beings rely on the brain
人類靠著大腦
Our athleticism is super
我們的運動能力是超強
making tools this is of course
製造工具這當然是
our most special
我們最特別的一點
in all tools
在所有的工具
Lens language and text should be the most special
鏡頭語言和文字應該是最特別的
I had a chat with Li Yuanshi during the meal just now
剛剛吃飯的時候跟李源氏也談了一下
Language is what we are born with
語言是我們天生的
Words were indeed invented by man
文字確實人發明的
same as science
跟科學一樣
something invented by everyone
所有人發明的東西
Usually it is not easy to learn
通常都不是一學就會
so kids
所以小孩子
Especially we can't write Chinese characters well
尤其是我們寫國字寫不好
Often used to be beaten
常常以前被打挨打手板
This hope that this teacher and the little
這個希望這個老師和小
Parents, don't often beat children's palms
這個爸媽媽們不要常常在去打小孩子手板
It should not be so easy for every child to learn to write
不應該是每一個小孩子學寫字那麼容易的
Humans actually have a very important stage
人類事實上有一個很重要的階段
It is an agricultural industry developed in collective life
是在集體生活裡頭發展出來的農業目業
I'll talk to you a little more later
我後面會跟大家稍微再多談一點
but one important thing
可是很重要一件事情
How we are different from other creatures
我們跟其他生物不一樣的地方
is apart from the human power that we have inherited
是除了遺傳給我們的人力以外
do we have a different part
我們是不是有一個不一樣的部分
the way we live
也就是我們生活的方式
traits that instill our existence
所陶於我們生存的特質
different from other creatures
跟其他的生物不太一樣
That's how our culture actually affects us
也就是我們的文化其實對我們的影響
Many places may be beyond our nature
很多地方也許超越了我們的本性
biological nature
生物本性
we have just mentioned
我們剛剛已經提到
If it is 15,000 to 30,000 years
如果是15000年到30,000年
It is human beings who have truly set foot on the
是人類真正正正的踏上了
the stage of evolution
這個演化的舞台
why do we say that
我們為什麼這樣去說呢
because during this time
因為在這段時間裡頭
Neanderthals disappeared from this earth
尼安德塔人從這個地球上消失了
About 30,000 years from now
大約就在距離現在30,000年
near
附近的時候
They entered the ice age with us
他們跟我們一起進到了冰河期
But there is no way out
可是卻沒有辦法走出來
Humans in 15,000 years
人類在15,000年
after the weather softens
天氣變軟了以後
Finally out of the ice age
終於走出了冰河時期
After this turn around, it will be incredible
這一翻身以後不得了
Let's take a look at the extent of the impact of this ice age
我們看一下這冰河時期的影響到什麼程度
The 18 means 18,000 years
那個18的地方是表示18,000年
That is, when the Ice Age has not fully receded
也就是冰河時期還沒有全退的時候
You look at all of Canada and the Great Lakes
你看整個加拿大和五大湖區
and the north of the United States
以及美國的北邊
This white area is full of ice lakes
這個白色區全是冰湖
all covered
全部覆蓋的
so in
所以在
The closest Ice Age to us
離我們最近的這次冰河時期
Between Mainland China and Taiwan
中國大陸和台灣之間
There is even a phenomenon of connection
甚至於有連結的現象
this is understandable
這是可以理解的
then say
然後說
this
這個
It's not just snowing, it's
不只下雪而已 而是
Base ice is already in mainland China
基冰已經在中國大陸
Accumulated to South China
累積到華南地區
base ice phenomenon
都有基冰的現象
It's not absolutely impossible
這也不是絕對不可能的
in fact
事實上
snow in the south
南部下雪
base ice maybe
基冰也許
There is no way the base is so thick
沒有辦法基到那麼厚
but you can watch
不過你可以看
Canada
它這整區的加拿大區
almost covered in ice
幾乎都被冰覆蓋了
If we look at the nearest 8000 years from now
那距離現在最近的8000年來看的話
it's already hiding
它就已經躲到了
I went to such a place
這麼一個地方去了
of course
那當然
now everyone is saying
以現在大家在說
This block of ice in the Arctic
北極區的這個冰塊
are under reduced
都在減少的情況之下
you just know
你就知道
why do you think
大家為什麼會覺得
very nervous
很緊張
good
好
pass
過了
After the Bianhe period, you see, this is 13,000 years
邊合時期以後 你看這是13000年
the reality of human development
人類在發展的實情的
Already there are very inverse and surprising tools
已經有非常逆能驚訝的工具出現
like this is an ancient needle
像這是一個古針
A needle made from a bone, you can see the meticulousness of its workmanship
骨頭磨出來的針 你看它的功夫的細緻性
On the surface, this piece seems to be the same as the period when the coincidence just made it
這一塊在表面上看起來好像跟剛剛巧人所做的那個時期
Stone knives are a little bit similar
石刀有那麼一點點相似
Actually, I'm sorry, it's still not the same
其實還是 對不起 還是不太一樣
Look at this piece, this is 4500 years
你看這一塊 這個是4500年
In 4500, a machine appeared in Dakengkeng, Taiwan
4500年 台灣的大坑坑已經有一機出現了
That's where Basian is now
也就是現在巴西安那個地方
I'm sorry, it should be the place of Badi
對不起 應該是巴底那個地方
Already some people's machines have appeared
已經有一些人的一機出現了
A piece of news I heard recently is
最近我聽到的一個新聞是
Matsu finds a bone that may be 7,000 years old
馬祖找到了一個距離現在可能是7000年的骨頭
that was a little earlier
那個是稍微再早一點的
You know that we already have colleagues and people in Asia
你就知道其實在我們亞洲也已經有同事有人
In Mexican words, in 4500 years
墨西哥的話 4500年的時候
You see this building is very beautifully done
你看這個建築是做得非常漂亮的
The grinding case of his bones and stones
他的骨頭和石頭的磨的情況
In fact, the 90s have already begun to move towards a new era
事實上90氣已經開始往新時期走了
So let's look ahead a little bit
所以我們稍微往前看一下
How did our people move forward?
到底我們的人是怎麼往前走的
Here I tell you a story
在這地方我跟大家講一個故事
We've reached the point where we're near the end
已經到了我們快遙尾端的地方
I tell you a story
我跟大家講一個故事
In fact the story was National Geographic
事實上這個故事是國家地理雜誌
I found it from an article in 2002
我從2002年的一篇文章裡頭找出來的
what he calls a lost civilization
他稱作消失的文明
But where did it disappear?
可是在哪裡消失呢
green sahara hard to imagine
綠色沙哈拉 很難想像
Why does the Sahara Desert use green to describe him?
為什麼沙哈拉沙漠要用綠色去形容他
The whole story happened in 2000
整個故事是發生在2000年的時候
At that time there was an archaeologist in Chicago
那個時候有一個芝加哥的考古學家
His name is Sireno
他的名稱叫做Sireno
this person is famous
這個人很有名
Because his discovery has been made into a movie
因為他的發現已經被拍成了電影
There's at least one movie called "All the Evil"
至少有一部電影叫做《金世俱惡》
Has anyone watched this movie
有人看過這部電影嗎
"The Evil Fish Thief"
《惡魚大盜》
10 times the movie of "Bad Fish" now
現在《惡魚》的10倍的電影
So about the size of a dinosaur
所以跟恐龍差不多大的
It was very surprising to find the crocodile in the salad
是非常令人驚訝在沙拉發現的鱷魚
There is also a species of grass dragon found in Nileir
另外還有一種在尼利日發現的一種草龍
This is what he found
這也是他發現的
He just happens to be familiar with that area.
正好他在那一區很熟悉
That's the Tarzan we'll mention later
也就是我們等一下要提的Tarzan
The Desert We Call Tethered
我們稱作太熱雷的沙漠
The story actually goes like this
這個故事事實上是這樣子
when they had an archaeological
在他們有一次考古的時候
Desert stability 120 degrees
沙漠穩度120度
Fahrenheit of course
當然是華氏
That's forty degrees now
也就是現在四十幾度
it's amazing temperature
這是驚人的溫度
They missed the exam for half a month
他們考漏考了半個月
found nothing
什麼都沒找到
Also encountered bandits in Africa
還遭遇到了非洲的強盜
At that time some of them got separated
那時候他們有些人走散掉了
there is a photographer
有一個攝影師
His name is Headware
他名稱叫做Headware
He found some kind-hearted human bones on a sand dune
他在一個沙丘上發現了一些善志的人骨
Now the words of the Tarzan desert
現在的Tarzan沙漠的話
we call it a desert within a desert
我們稱它作沙漠中的沙漠
that is to say
也就是表示
Almost the driest area
幾乎是最乾燥的一個區域了
what did headware say
Headware說了一句什麼話
He said it seemed like there was a gust of wind in the desert
他說好像有沙漠上有一陣風
brought us to that place
把我們帶到了那個地方
let's rest in that place
讓我們休息在那個地方
But immediately on that side
可是立刻在那一方
He found something very unusual
他發現了很不尋常的事情
In the tools he found the real thing, the building, the axe.
在公具裡頭他找到了實器 建築 斧頭
Then the bone he found a lot of bone
然後骨頭他找到了很多的受骨
Including Lingyang's scenes of deer and aquatic animals
包括靈陽的 場景鹿的 水生動物的
Among them are crocodiles, hippos, turtles, and fish sticks.
其中有鱷魚 河馬 龜 魚棒
Why in the desert in such a dry desert
為什麼會在這麼乾的沙漠中的沙漠裡頭
find something like this
找到像這樣子的東西
Includes bones and osteoids
包括了骨頭和可類 骨類的東西
sirino he is worthy of being an archaeologist
Sirino他不愧為是一個考古學家
He is so fine that he is likely to stand in a place where he used to be
他精絕到他很可能站在一個以前這個地方
was once a plant
曾經是有植物的植
or at least the biological part
或者至少有生物的部分
in fact on the stony ground
事實上在石頭地上
You can still see that there are carvings out
你還是可以看到有雕刻出來的
Carved out of this scene is the scene of a deer
刻出來的這個場景鹿的景象
So is there really a lot of creatures in that place?
所以是不是那個地方真的有很多的生物
live in that place
活在那個地方
Okay, let's talk about the Green Desert first.
好 我們先談綠色沙漠
In fact, 70,000 years ago
事實上距離現在七萬年前
It's almost our kind of intelligence
也差不多就是我們這種智能
Start making one of the most important thousand joys on earth
在地球上開始做一個最重要的千喜
When we talk about the process of flying from east to east or west to Qianxi
我們說從東飛往東或者西千喜的過程的時候
At that time the salad desert was in fact
那個時候沙拉沙漠事實上
its axis at that time
它在那個時候地軸
70,000 years ago it was actually a desert
七萬年前的時候事實上是沙漠
But 12,000 years ago
不過在一萬兩千年前的時候
its axis actually wobbled a bit
它的地軸事實上搖擺了一下
In other words, after the Ice Age
也就是說在冰河時期過了以後
12,000 years ago there was a swing
一萬兩千年前的時候搖擺了一下
The wind from Africa during that swing
那一次搖擺時的非洲的寄風
suddenly move north
突然之間往北移
That is, its rainfall suddenly shifts northward.
也就是它的雨量突然之間往北移
That is to say, many places in the whole area
也就是這整區很多地方
There is abundant rainfall
通通有豐沛的雨量
What is the result of this abundant rainfall?
這個豐沛的雨量造成什麼樣的結果呢
You can watch these two pieces
你可以看這兩塊
From this point of view
以這一塊來看的話
We usually like the light yellow area here
我們通常像這邊的淺黃色的區域的話
the grassland we live in
我們身處的草原
this proportional angle
這個比例角
If this place is green, like this dark green
綠的這個地方 像這種深綠的話
is the rainforest
就是雨林
Shallower, this place is said to be a grassland
淺一點這個地方說是草原
Now barely
現在勉勉強強的話
This place is probably still grass
這個地方大概還算是有草
This yellow place is all desert
這個黃的地方就全部是沙漠了
So we are talking about the area away from the green
所以我們現在在講的離綠的區域
It's this place called Gerborough
就是這個叫做葛伯洛的地方
red dot this place
紅點的這個地方
totally yellow
完全是黃色的
so currently it's desert
所以目前它是沙漠
70,000 years ago, it was also a desert
七萬年以前的時候也是沙漠
But twelve thousand years ago
可是在一萬兩千年以前
became like this
變成了這個樣子
that is its place
也就是它這塊地方
turned into a light green area
變成了淺綠區
That is, a place with grassland
也就是具有草原的地方
So in other words the Gerborough area
所以換句話說葛伯洛地區
In fact, there are green areas that are very dark green.
其實是有綠地很深綠的
not only
不只如此
In fact NASA even sent this space shuttle
事實上NASA還派了這個太空梭
Go to the photo taken above
到著上面去照出來的照片
So the same is in the desert on the desert
所以同樣的是在沙漠上漠的地方
You can see the remains of the river beneath the ground
你可以看到地底下有河流的遺跡
so there are very wide rivers
所以有非常寬的河流
flow period
流過期間
you can see it along the top of the bed
你可以看到它的沿床上面
In fact, some of the river dormitory
事實上有被河川寢室的一些
How long ago did this happen
這個現象在多久年前
Back in the desert 3,500 years ago
3500年前回到了沙漠的時候
so we are now familiar
所以我們現在很熟悉
The Chinese often say Shahai Shangtian, Shahai Shangtian
中國人常常說沙海商田 沙海商田
in fact the whole world
事實上全世界都是如此
There have been humans on the earth for 3500 years
3500年地球上已經有人類了
then he started drying again
那他又開始變乾了
so what's going on over there
所以那邊挖出了什麼事情
Let's see in 2005
我們看看在2005年
he went back to that place
他又回到那個地方去
This time it's not just him
這次不只他一個人
In fact another named Anna
事實上另外一個叫Anna
go with him
陪他一起去
Anna is actually an anthropologist
Anna事實上是一個人類學家
when going with him
跟他一起去的時候
More human wills found
找到了更多的人類的遺囑
found two batches
找到了兩批
it's something special
這是很特別的事情
These two chains
這兩批鏈頭
one batch of time
其中一批時間
It should be about 4,000 to 6,000 years
應該就是差不多四千多年到六千多年
Four thousand years to six thousand years from now
距離現在四千多年到六千多年
They probably have mother races
他們大概是有母民族
But another group earlier
可是另外一批更早
The time is about 8,000 to 10,000 years
時間差不多在八千年到一萬年
Ten thousand years is a very special number
一萬年是一個很特別的一個數字
their life is not oily wood
他們生活不是油木
they live by hunting
他們靠狩獵為生
So the way of life is very different
所以生活的方式非常不一樣
flyers
他們稱作祈飛人
That's why it's called the Tyranids
所以這邊稱作泰倫人
Prayers
這邊稱作祈飛人
The two times are not the same
兩個時間不太一樣
where is the difference
差別在哪裡呢
If it is closer to the present
如果是以距離現在比較近的
If the Tyranids come to see
泰倫人來看的話
they are smaller
他們體型比較小
The front of the skull is higher
頭骨的話前面比較高
they can have some funeral things
他們可以有一些陪葬的事物
like this is a volcanic stone
像這是火山的石頭
And some crimes done with hippo bones
還有用河馬的骨頭做的一些罪事
At least they probably ran to
他們起碼是可能跑到了
volcanic fields hundreds of miles away
幾百里以外的火山區域
pick up some jade
撿回來一些玉石
but not sure
可是也不太確定
Or trade with others
還是跟人家交易來的
still picked it up
還是撿回來的
not sure
這不是很確定
but one thing is certain
可是很確定的一件事情
their stone kisses
他們的石吻頭
There is already a phenomenon of penning sheep and cattle
已經有圈羊牛隻的現象
The other is the flyer
另外一種是祈飛人
look at their tools
你看他們的工具
yes can have
是可以有
With a hook, this hook is also very delicate, isn't it?
有魚鉤的 這個魚鉤也是很精緻 對嗎
I said its time is between 8,000 and 10,000
我說過它的時間在不在8000到1萬
It's a lot to find and then you can look at its harpoon
是找得多的 然後你們可以看它的魚叉
It is also done quite delicately, using the current science
也是做得相當的精緻 那用現在的科學
Especially if you look at it with chemical analysis, you can see
尤其是化學分析法去看的話 可以看出來
Some of their living habits and diseases, for example, judging from their teeth
他們的一些生活習性和疾病 譬如說從他們牙齒來看的話
They've started chewing some crude bone
他們已經開始有嚼一些粗造的骨類
Thick bone, not our current Pongalmi
粗的骨 不是我們現在的Pongalmi
Obviously those sorghum or some thicker bones
顯然是那些什麼高粱 或者是更粗的一些骨類
If most of them are consecutive records, it is difficult to live beyond the age of 40
那大部分是連記的話 很難活到超過40歲
From the franc implant of the tooth, a silk isotope can be found
從牙齒的法郎植上面 可以找到一個絲的同位數
That is, the same digit of the silk margin number, if we do dating analysis
也就是絲緣數的同位數 做定年分析的話
It can be known that they must drink fresh water
可以知道他們一定有喝淡水的情況
And fresh water must be available for father to drink
而且淡水一定是在父親可以喝得到的
They don't have to travel very far to tell from their bones
他們不需要走很遠的路 是從他們的骨骼就可以判斷
You will find that anthropology uses many chemical analysis methods
你會發現現在人類學用了許許多多的化學分析法
Bioanalysis can know all the situations of their lives
生物分析法可以知道他們所有生活的情況
Judging from the bones of fish or shellfish they left behind
從他們所留下來的魚類或者貝類的骨頭來看的話
They actually caught the Furnace Monster of the Nile
他們其實有抓到尼羅河的爐怪
I don't know what the furnace monster of the Nile didn't know
我不知道尼羅河的爐怪原來不知道是什麼樣子
You can only see it when you watch a movie in National Geographic magazine recently
最近看國家地理雜誌的電影才可以看到
Some fish in the Nile are actually more than a few meters long
尼羅河裡頭有些魚其實是超過幾公尺長的
very large fish belonging to the class of furnace fish
非常大的魚 屬於爐魚類的
Of course it also has other crocodiles and hippos
當然它還有其他的鱷魚和河馬
These things all go together
這些事情都連在一起了
I am a little bit moved by the fact that the Chinese say that a gentleman is in the end of the world, but he does not hide his name
我有點感慨的是 中國人說 君子極末世 名而不藏
But knowing the name sometimes doesn't help
可是事實上知道名字有的時候也沒什麼用
If you don't know the name, now dig out the bones
名字不知道的話 現在把骨頭挖出來以後
After turning over the book, I can clearly see all the days I lived in the past
翻了老本 以前過的什麼日子通通都看得清清楚楚
You can probably find out anything you've done.
做過什麼事情大概都可以找出來
In the end is a person living
到底是一個人生存中
Is it important for the survival of the group
還是群體的生存重要
Is the process important or the result important?
到底是過程重要還是結果重要
in front of nature
在大自然的面前
the ruthlessness of nature
大自然的無情
but we are also
可是我們同時也是
live by nature
以來大自然而生存
so I often feel
所以我常常感慨
Life is often dependent on nature
生命常常是需要靠大自然
provide opportunity
提供機會
But nature does not guarantee us
可是大自然不給我們保證
This sentence has been used by me often
這一句話已經被我常常拿來
used in education
用在教育裡頭
I think the most important thing about education
我認為教育最重要的事情
It should be the principal of the school
應該是學校的校長也好
Whether it is the director or the teacher
主任也好 老師也好
should be available to those who study
應該要提供給學習的人
Good environment
好的環境
For example, in college
譬如說在大學裡頭的話
Principals should be responsible for creating an environment
校長應該負責打造一個環境
Let professors do research well
讓教授可以好好地做研究
The professor should create a good
教授應該打造一個好的
laboratory environment or classroom environment
實驗室的環境或課堂的環境
Let students learn well
讓學生可以好好地學習
So create the environment, create the opportunity
所以創造環境 創造機會
but no guarantee
可是不提供保證
Because no one after finishing college
因為沒有一個人大學念完了以後
This life is a life
這一輩子就是一生順態
it shouldn't be this kind of thing
應該不會是這種事情
but take a look
不過大概看一看
Qi Feiren
齊飛人
Why are you still staying in Gerbero in eight thousand years?
什麼八千年的時候還留在葛伯洛
But there is no way when Gerbero lives for more than 4,000 years
卻沒有辦法在葛伯洛活到四千多年的時候
According to the logic, Gerbero District should have been around 3,500 years ago
照道理 葛伯洛區應該是在三千五百年的時候
It was turned into a desert area again
才重新變成沙漠區域的
So what kind of environmental changes are they
所以他們是什麼樣的環境變化
making them lose their ability to survive there
使得他們失去了在那邊求生的能力
this is a question worth asking
這個是值得問的問題
Some people say that self is also our modern self
有人說 自人也就是我們的現代自人
Bing and Zizi
是兵和自子
But we're up to now and we're going to ask one thing
可是我們到現在我們會問一件事情
Why do people who come out of Bing and many
為什麼從兵和很多出來的人
Everyone's fate is different
每一個人的命運不太一樣
Some feet live longer and some feet live shorter
有些足 活著時間長 有些足 活著時間短
For example, this one is Australian
譬如說像這一張是澳洲人
Australians now know
澳洲人據現在瞭解
Before Europeans moved to Australia more than a hundred years ago
在歐洲人一百多年前移到澳洲區之前
They've been there for 40,000 years
他們在那邊已經待了四萬年
For 40,000 years, their lives have not changed much at all.
四萬年他們的生活完全沒有什麼太大的變化
Still a hunter's life a gatherer's life
仍然是狩獵的生活 採集的生活
But more than a hundred years ago
可是一百多年前
After the Europeans went in, they completely turned them over
歐洲人進去以後 整個把他們翻了盤
We may ask why the social shadow of human beings
我們會問 為什麼人類的社會影頭
It was Europeans who discovered America and Australia
是歐洲人發現了美洲和澳洲
Not Indians or Australians discovered Europe
而不是印第安人或澳洲人發現了歐洲
I just mentioned the book by Jerr Diamond
我剛剛提到Jerr Diamond這本書
He said how the fate of mankind actually happened
他說 人類的命運到底是如何發生的
This book is guns germs and steel
這本書是槍砲 細菌和鋼鐵
Should be available now
應該現在還可以買得到
It's the textbook I use for my general studies
是我用來上我的通識課的教科書
he gave me good answers
他給了我很好的答案
A question I started asking around 40
我大概在40歲的時候開始問的一個問題
He gave me a lot of good inspiration in this book
他在這本書裡頭給了我很多的很好的啟發
So I also introduce to you
所以我同時介紹給大家
We've just heard about the Inca Empire
剛剛我們已經聽到印加帝國了
Why are there so many glorious ancient civilization empires
為什麼有很多的很輝煌的古文明帝國
Can't live on in history
不能夠歷史永傳
Why the Civilizations of Western Europe Pray Big Today
今天為什麼西歐的文明大型祈禱
Why Western Europe invented science and technology
為什麼西歐發明的科學和科技
Is able to be chased by people all over the world
是能夠為全世界的人都在追逐
See Jerr Diamond mentioned a story
看看Jerr Diamond提到一個故事
This story doesn't really need him to tell us.
這個故事其實不需要他來跟我們講
Because if we just pay attention to the history of South America
因為只要稍微注意一下南美洲的歷史的話
you can notice a story like this
就可以注意到這樣的故事
when the Incas were before the Europeans came in
印加人在歐洲人進去之前的時候
It's actually really brilliant
實際確實非常的輝煌的
General Pizarro of Spain
西班牙的皮薩羅將軍
In fact, when it came to the Inca Empire, it happened to be in
事實上到印加帝國的時候剛好是在
columbus
哥倫布
Not long after discovering America
發現了美洲沒有太久
in the 16th century
16世紀的時候
when pizarro passed by
皮薩羅過去的時候
On the plateau of Miru
密魯的高原上
Cajamarca was actually their Inca capital
卡哈馬卡事實上是他們的印加首都
At that time the king was called Atahuapura
那個時候的國王叫做阿塔華普拉
his soldiers
他的兵
He has eighty thousand soldiers
他的兵有八萬
He has no soldiers, he only has soldiers because
他沒有兵馬他只有兵因為
no horses in south america
南美洲沒有馬
only
只有
camel horses don't really have no horses as we see them now
駝馬沒有真的沒有現在我們看的馬
Pizarro only brought you can imagine
皮薩羅只帶了你能夠想像嗎
more than three hundred people
三百多個人
Troops
兵困馬伐
People of Wuhe
烏河之眾
He splits
他兵分兩路
62 cavalry plus 106 infantry
62個騎兵加上了106個步兵
no expense one foot
不費一兵一足
Atahuapura
就活捉了阿塔華普拉
then they
然後他們
After Zi De asked for about 60 cubic meters of gold
紫德索了大約60立方米的黃金以後
He still killed Atahuapra
他還是把阿塔花普拉促死了
Europeans are brutal
歐洲人蠻狠的
This war has become irresistible in the end
這個戰爭到後來勢如破竹
The Inca Empire will never fight
印加帝國就一絕不爭
So in this book
所以在這本書裡頭
Jer Diamond mentioned why Europe is like this
Jer Diamond提到為什麼歐洲會這樣子
Defeat the Inca Empire
把印加帝國打得一絕不爭
the whole collapse
整個崩潰掉
he mentioned something
他提到一些事情
Since the development of agriculture and wood industry in Mesopotamia in Europe,
歐洲自從兩河流域發展了農業和木業以後
spread to continental Europe
傳到了歐洲大陸去
allowed Europe to have an earlier time
使得歐洲有比較早的時間
have a larger population
就有比較多的人口
Developed more effective imperial politics
發展出比較有效的帝國的政治
And their cities are more complex
而且他們的城市也比較複雜
Their function is in terms of the government system
他們的功能在政府的體制上面來講
In terms of organizational structure
組織的體制上來講
can be seen from their cities
都可以從他們城市看得出來
Like Rome, for example, you can see that
譬如說像羅馬你就可以看出來是
very systematic
非常的有制度
Of course this caused their army to be professional
當然這造成了他們的軍隊是需要專業的
technology needs professional
技術是需要專業的
Craftsmanship requires professionalism
工藝是需要專業的
All manufacture guns and swords
所有製造槍砲刀劍
And there is the use of steel
而且有鋼鐵的使用
So from these perspectives
所以從這些方面來看
Europe has long been on the tools of civilization
歐洲早就在文明的工具上
great strides
跨了很大的步子
And the horse batch found in Central Asia
而且在中亞找到的馬批
Make it more than just plowing the fields
使得不只是可以耕田而已
They are very effective in combat
他們在作戰方面非常的有效
This is something that America doesn't have
這個都是美洲沒有的東西
America's empire is also divided
美洲的帝國也有分裂的狀態
the most serious is
最嚴重的就是
Germs brought to America by Europeans
歐洲人帶到美洲去的病菌
Includes Smallpox and Metu
包括了天花和梅圖
make Europeans fully
使得歐洲人完全
making South Americans completely immune
使得南美人完全沒有免疫力
almost defeated
幾乎是兵敗如山倒
All of a sudden it's just a disease
一下子光是疾病
thousands died
就成千上萬的死掉
There are a few other important things
其他還有幾件重要的事情
Including dissemination of text and information
包括了文字和資訊的傳播
and social system
以及社會制度
manpower against different people
對付不同的人的人力
and thinking habits are different
以及思考的習慣都不一樣
It shows that when two cultures meet
表示了兩種文化在相遇的時候
Culture may not be good or bad
文化可能沒有優劣
But there are strengths and weaknesses
可是有強勢和弱勢
this is reality
這是現實
So there are two more important things
所以有兩件比較重要的事情
one is text
一個是文字
We just said that the Inca didn't have a very effective script
我們剛剛說印加沒有很有效的文字
They have language but no writing
他們有語言可是沒有文字
So actually their history has no foundation.
所以其實他們的歷史是沒有根基的
Not so in Europe
可是歐洲不是如此
texts and their dissemination of information
文字以及他們的資訊傳播
In fact, they have long since made them socially
事實上早就使他們整個社會上
History, economy, and various systems are already very developed
歷史 經濟 各種的制度都已經非常的發達了
So we said why didn't the Indians go to Europe
所以我們說為什麼不是印第安人跑到歐洲去
In fact, as Europe entered the Americas,
事實上隨著歐洲進到了美洲的時候
They're past the time of the renaissance
他們已經過了文藝復興的時間
all habits of thought
所帶出來的所有思考的習慣
We have entered the age of science
已經進到了科學時代了
ok let's see the best
好 我們看最好的
The last few pictures are done, it's already 90 minutes
最後的幾張做結束了 已經到90分鐘了
You'll find in plants and animals we say agriculture and wood
你會發現在植物和動物 我們說農業和木業
When this wheat and rice was first made
最早把這個小麥稻米做出來的時候
Wheat was indeed in Mesopotamia 8,500 years ago
小麥的確就是在兩河流域 8500年
In Chinese words, rice is 7500 years old
在中國的話 稻米 7500年
Then sheep and horses, horses were not domesticated until 3000 years ago in Central Asia
然後羊 馬 馬是在中亞地區 3000年的時候才被馴服
So you'll find that not everywhere
所以你會發現 不是在每一個地方
All have good food, all have good farming
通通都有好的食物 都有好的農作
There are good sheep herding environments everywhere, or there are flowing horses and sheep everywhere.
通通都有好的牧羊的環境 或者是流馬羊到處都有
Not so of course it can spread
不是如此的 當然它可以傳播
But the environment is not the same everywhere
可是不是到處的地方的環境都一樣
so what does it enlighten me about at the unit door
所以就在單元門它對我啟發了什麼東西呢
Malthus once said
馬爾薩斯說過一句話說
You actually when the population in your environment increases rapidly
你事實上當你的環境裡頭 人口快速增加的時候
food around you
你周圍能夠有的食物
food is about to decrease
食物馬上就要減少
After the food is reduced
食物一減少以後
The population may not be able to increase very quickly
人口可能就不能夠很快的增加
So this is actually mutually restrictive
所以這個事實上互相限制的
But it may overlook one thing
可是它可能忽略了一件事情
After the industrial revolution
就是工業革命了以後
Because mechanical force replaces human power, there is still force
機械力因為取代了人力還有受力
so the personnel changed
所以人員改變了
In terms of people we have taken out from the natural world
我們已經從自然界引頭取出來的人員來講
At that time began to be able to dig a lot of coal
那個時候開始能夠挖出大量的煤
generate steam and operate the machine
產生蒸氣而且操作機器了
in this case
在這種情況之下
you will find one very important thing
你會發現很重要一件事情
This may be my most critical header video of the day
這可能是我今天最關鍵的一張頭影片的
A noun called Karen Capacity
一個名詞叫做Karen Capacity
What is Karen Capacity?
什麼叫Karen Capacity呢
It's just how many people can an environment support?
就是一個環境到底可以養多少人
There is no standard answer
這沒有一個標準答案的
We can ask the same question
我們同樣問題可以問
How many people can Taiwan's resources support?
台灣的資源到底可以養多少人
Can support 23 million
可以養2300萬啊
No problem at all
當然沒問題
Because we now have 23 million people living here
因為我們現在2300萬人活在這邊
OK
OK
That can support 30 million
那可以養3000萬
or 50 million
或者5000萬嗎
If there are too few people
那如果人太少的話
Do we have enough manpower?
我們的人力夠不夠呢
so this is a very important concept
所以這是一個很重要的概念
Malthus made a statement
馬爾薩斯提出來一句話
He said that if the population exceeds
他說如果人口超過了
If this is the maximum population that can be maintained
這個能夠維持的最大人口量的話
The changes that will occur to the environment
那對環境就會產生的改變
The population will probably decrease
人口大概就會減少
but he may not have noticed something
可是他可能沒有注意到一些事情
The use of personnel will actually change the resource
人員的使用其實會改變資源的
we just mentioned
我們剛剛前面提到
Interchange of personnel and materials
人員和物資的互變
Actually we are in this world
其實我們在這個世界上
by what we just said
靠著我們剛剛說
Materials produced by different personnel
不同的人員所產生出來的物資
It's actually pretty amazing
其實是非常驚人的
In fact, in the second century
事實上二世紀的時候
chemist proposes oil industry
化學家提出了石油工業
Like this, it's medium oil
像這個的話是中油
This is probably Liuqing
這個大概是六清
This should be the flower oil machine of the sea
這個應該是海上的花油的機器
You can also see another one from the second century
你也可以看到二世紀另外一個
nuclear power of course
當然就是核能
This should also be our third nuclear plant
這個應該也是我們的核三廠
what does it bring
它帶來的是什麼呢
Let's look at this population curve
我們看一下這個人口曲線
the red one is
紅色的這個是
if your death rate is too high
如果你的死亡率太高的話
it can level off quickly
它可以很快就平了
But if your mortality
可是如果你的死亡率
not too high
不至於太高情況之下
if it maintains normal growth
它維持正常成長的話
rush up soon
很快就往上衝
So in terms of heavy axis
所以以重軸來講的話
Here is almost what we see
這邊差不多是我們看
this time in this place
這個時間在這個地方
We are currently around 2010
我們目前是2010附近
almost here
差不多在這裡
so the place is about
所以這個地方大約是
7 billion people
70億的人口
It should be 10 billion
應該是這是100億
So 10 billion down
所以100億下來
90 80 70
90 80 70
around here
差不多在這附近
So we're probably here
所以我們目前大概在這裡
So many people have been troubled for a while
所以很多人好一陣子困擾
where are we going
我們會往什麼方向走
probably current economists
大概現在的經濟學家
and this human resource to the world
以及這個對世界的人資源
more familiar
比較了解的
will tell us
會告訴我們
We'll probably go the purple route
我們大概會走這條紫色的路線
that is likely to go
也就是很可能會走
In this century, the population will exceed 10 billion
在這個世紀裡頭突破100億人口
In fact, based on our record
事實上以我們的紀錄來看
look at this one
你看這一張
The current world population exceeded 700 million at the end of last year
目前的世界人口數在去年年底突破7億
in the last century
上一個世紀的時候
In fact, just before the Second World War, it was just over 3 billion
其實在第二次大戰之前的時候才剛過30億
So the doubling speed is very fast
所以加倍的速度是非常的快的
The yellow one is to develop the country
黃色的這個是以開發國家
They were in fact during World War II
他們事實上在第二次世界大戰的時候
The population has started to decline
人口已經開始往下走了
When will the population of developing countries start to decline?
開發中國家什麼時候人口才會往下開始走呢
At least it will start slowly after 2000
起碼要在2000年之後才會慢慢開始
Only then will we start going down from this place
才會從這個地方開始往下走
Therefore, the population of developed countries in the world
所以這個世界上以開發的國家人口數
as a proportion of the population of developing countries
和開發中國家人口的比例
In fact, the proportion of developing countries is still very high
事實上開發中國家比例佔的還是非常的高
At least as far as the BRIC countries are concerned
至少金磚四國來講的話
BRIC means Brazil, Russia and India and China
金磚四國表示是巴西、俄國和印度和中國
The population of these four countries
這四個國家佔的人口數
should probably be
應該大概就
more than half of the world's population
就超過全世界人口數的一半以上
because it was found that a large population
因為發現有大量的人口
he's gonna really start falling
他要真正開始下降
in fact it will take a while
事實上還要一段時間
we said earlier
我們前面是說
staff may not be adequate
人員可能不是充分夠用的
Based on our current population
那以我們現在人口
human lifespan
人類的壽命來看
In fact, there are several curves here
其實這邊也有幾個曲線
we can pay attention
我們可以注意一下
The most controllable is
最能夠控制的是
use of personnel
人員的使用
If used in a valid situation
如果使用到有效的情況之下
immediately have access to your technology
就馬上可以利用你的高科技
to control health problems
去控制衛生問題
The most important hygiene should be drinking water
最重要的衛生應該是飲水
If drinking water can be controlled
如果飲水可以控制住的話
your contagious disease
你傳染性的疾病
if you get it under control
馬上控制住的話
You'll see the death rate drop immediately
你會發現死亡率立刻下降下來
death rate drop
死亡率下降
The birth rate also fell
出生率也跟著下降
In fact, after the death rate dropped
事實上死亡率下降了以後
it's probably closer to ten percent of this place
它大概接近來百分之十的這個地方
nearest west
最近的西方
You can see it doing the second wave of descent
你可以看到它在做第二波的下降
what is the disease it wants to control
它想控制的疾病是什麼呢
is a chronic disease
是慢性疾病
I have this disease too
這種疾病我也有
reached a certain age
到了一定的年紀
Probably neovascular disease and high blood pressure
大概都是新血管疾病和血壓過高
Three high questions
三高的這些問題
If chronic disease can be controlled
如果慢性疾病可以控制的話
The death rate can be lowered
死亡率可以降得更低
If you put developing and country
如果你把開發中和國家
To make a comparison with developing countries
以開發中國家來做一個比較的話
in terms of birth rate
在出生率以頭來看
in terms of developing the country
以開發國家的話
In fact, in the last century
事實上在上一個世紀的時候
You will find that its death rate is already falling
你會發現它的死亡率已經在往下掉
But if it is a developing country
可是如果是以開發中國家的話
Its mortality rate is actually going to this century
它的死亡率事實上是要到這個世紀
just started falling from here
才從這個地方開始往下掉
So to represent the population of the world
所以表示這個世界上的人口
Should be walking up for a while
應該還要在往上走一陣子
Probably can't escape until 101
到101年大概躲不掉
You will find different country desk
你會發現不同的國家案頭
Survival and survival strategies are different
生存和生活的策略是不同的
The last few three slides
最後的幾張三張投影片
I will talk about this topic
我會講這個題目
because i just said
是因為我剛剛說
Scientists actually look at things with a scope
科學家其實看事情是要有一個scope
That is to say, the target of your research
也就是說你要研究的目標
In fact, there must be a specific goal
其實是要有特定的目標的
see things very precisely
看事情很精準的
But today we also found something
可是今天我們也發現一件事情
Just use technology to see things
光是用技術去看事情
Sometimes it may not be enough
可能有的時候不是很夠
Because what we live in this world is as a person
因為我們在這個世界上活的是身為一個人
If you look at things from a human point of view
用人的角度去看事情的話
may be different
可能不太一樣
Jerr Diamond he gave me the answer is also good
Jerr Diamond他所給我的答案也好
problem is good
問題也好
that's it
就是如此
I list him one by one
我把他一條一條的列出來
Please take a look with me
請大家跟我看一下
He said every civilization and every culture
他說每一個文明和每一個文化
not necessarily immortal
不見得都能夠永垂不朽
In fact, this is what we all want
其實這是我們大家所希望的
Chinese culture is very difficult, especially hope
華人文化很頭尤其會希望
Our children can obey the three rights
我們的子女能夠服路受三權
Is it right
對嗎
Which of us doesn't wish for ourselves
我們哪一個人不希望我們自己
As long as our children can obey the road and accept the three powers
就我們的子女都能夠服路受三權
But he tells us that every civilization and every civilization
可是他告訴我們每一個文明和每一個文明
Every culture may not be immortal
每一種文化未必都能夠永垂不朽
Not every civilization has been around for a long time
不是每一個文明時間久了
can be compared from a
都可以從一個比較
on the face of it
表面上看來
tools life aspects
工具 生活 各方面
relatively backward
都比較落後的情況
progress will develop
會發展出進步的情況
This does not mean any discrimination
這個沒有任何的歧視意味
For example, I just said Australia
你譬如說我剛說了澳洲
With no one competing with him in that place
在那個地方沒有人跟他競爭的情況之下
Isolated from this world for 40,000 years
隔絕這個世界四萬年之久
After entering Europe, the whole turnaround
歐洲進去以後整個翻盤
so not any civilization
所以不是任何一個文明
They must all go forward in a straight line or a curve.
都一定照著一個直線或曲線往前走的
not absolute
不是絕對的
Many tools, some difficult and some easy
很多的工具有的難有的容易
It is more difficult as we just said
像我們剛剛講的比較難的
It was invented by humans themselves
是人類自己發明出來的
For example, it is difficult to say words
譬如說文字很難
science is hard
科學很難
These are not learned by everyone
這些都不是每一個人一學就會的
So not everyone enters school
所以不是每一個人進了學校以後
Both exams should have the same high marks
考試都應該一樣高分的
This is worth every Taiwan
這個是值得台灣每一個
People who engage in education pay attention
搞教育的人稍微注意一下
There are not many opportunities for real innovation in many things
很多事情真正創新的機會不多
many manufactured things
很多製造出來的東西
Many people learn from others
很多人是跟別人學的
did not invent
不是自己發明的
But there's nothing wrong with learning from others.
可是跟人家學也沒有什麼不好啊
The development of much of our knowledge
我們很多知識的發展
many ways of thinking
很多思考的方式
i just said
我剛剛講過
Especially when it comes to things like words and science
尤其是像文字和科學這種東西的話
Someone invented it first
有人先發明出來了
let's learn
我們去學
well-educated and poorly-learned
學得好和學得不好
Depends on our talent and hard work
要看我們的天分和努力
But he said something
可是他講了一句話
Whoever runs first is not necessarily the winner
先跑的不一定是贏家
Winning now may not always win
現在贏的也不一定永遠贏
I often say this
這句話我常常在講
is worth our vigilance
是值得我們警惕的
Whoever runs first doesn't necessarily win.
先跑的人真的不一定贏啊
because if you look at
因為你如果看
The earliest places where agriculture developed
農業發展的最早的地方
Youwa language
養和留語
messed up now
現在一塌糊塗
If it weren't for the private oil produced elsewhere
如果不是因為他地方產私油的話
Hold on to other places first
他地方先持上
The situation in the Middle East lives in many places
中東的情況生活很多地方
Of course he also has
當然他也有
very rich people there
非常有錢的人在那裡
then you go to africa
然後你去看非洲
Africa is not the best place to live
非洲不是一個生活的情況最好的地方
In fact, the most starved to death every day is also in Africa
事實上每天餓死的最多的也是在非洲
Those who win now may not always win
那現在贏的也不一定永遠贏
Of course, the current winners may also become losers.
當然現在的贏的也可能是有可能變成輸家的
But those who destroy their own resources are always the losers
可是破壞自身資源的永遠是輸家
Because civilizations that disappeared like this have already appeared on the earth several times
因為這樣子消失的文明在地球上已經出現好幾個了
That's what I just said maybe this paragraph
這就是我剛剛說可能是這一段
The most important sentence at the beginning of today's speech
今天演講頭最關鍵的一句話
Once any kind of life is developed
任何一種的生命一旦發展出來了
When breaking through the technical civilization of carrying capacity
突破carrying capacity的技術文明的時候
may have to accept the challenge of a personnel crisis
可能就必須接受人員危機的挑戰
In other words, when we have developed such a sophisticated technology
換句話說像我們發展出來了這麼高明的科技的時候
we need enough people and supplies
我們就需要足夠的人員和物資
to support the increased population we need
來支持我們所需要增加的人口
and the technologies we develop
以及我們所發展的科技
it's necessary
這是必要的
But have we noticed what we consume
可是我們有沒有注意到所消耗的東西
there is no chance to fill
是沒有添補的機會的
Probably everyone in Taiwan should notice
可能在台灣的每一個人都應該要注意到
We have exhausted the resources of our descendants
我們已經把我們後代子孫的資源都已經用掉了
An Evolutionary Perspective Head of Nature
在演化的角度來看 大自然的頭
Humans are not the center of this natural world most of the time
人類大部分時間不是這個自然界的中心
Will we be the center of the world in the future?
將來我們是不是一定是這個世界的中心
Not necessarily, right?
也不一定 對嗎
The emergence of humans may be an accident of nature on earth
人類出現可能是大自然地球上的一個偶發事件
Evolution does not have a definite direction
演化不是有確定的方向的
Maybe we just took an opportunity
可能我們只是抓到了一個機會出現而已
If we look at our current human beings in this world
如果看我們目前在人類在這個世界上
Its time is actually only tens of thousands of years
它的時間其實只有幾萬年
We have evidence to back our time up to only a few tens of thousands of years
我們有證據可以支持我們的只有幾萬年的時間
There is a natural law, a biological context, and an environmental context
有自然的規律 有生物的脈絡 有環境的脈絡
it has a background
它有一個背景
brought us to where we are today
使得我們發展到今天這種情形
can we think about it
我們是不是可以想一想
When biological evolution has no way to move forward effectively
當生物的演化已經沒有辦法很有效的往前走的時候
Changes in our environment and changes in our culture
我們的環境的變化以及我們文化的變化
Is it when we live in this world
是不是我們在這個世界上生存的時候
special attention should be paid
應該格外注意的
In other words how do we live
換句話說我們怎麼過日子
and how the people around us live
以及我們周圍的人怎麼過日子
Should it become the focus of our thinking?
是不是應該變成我們思考的重點
Of course, this is what I often tell my students in class
當然這是我常常跟我學生在課堂上講的
Now that we have stood on this stage of nature
我們既然已經站在了這個大自然的舞台上面
after thinking about it
有思考過後
And thinking about the manpower of tomorrow
又有思考明天以後的人力的話
So should we be responsible for tomorrow?
那我們是不是應該要為明天負責
Responsible for the environment and culture
也為環境與文化負責
A lot of questions were when Jerr Diamond read that book
好多的問題是Jerr Diamond讀那本書的時候
I'm asking
我在問的
How can life on earth last forever?
地球上生命怎麼樣才能夠永續呢
what kind of environment to live in
要生存在什麼樣的環境
What kind of environment do we live in?
我們是生存在什麼樣的環境裡頭呢
what are we
我們究竟
what kind of creature is it
是什麼樣的生物呢
You will find that if other creatures
你會發現如果是其他的生物
For example, a goldfish that landed in the Pacific Ocean
譬如說落在太平洋的金魚
Did he know he was near an island
他知不知道他是靠近了一個海島
or near the west coast of a Pacific Ocean
或靠近了一個太平洋的西岸
probably not
可能不會
But we are concerned about our environment
可是我們是對我們的環境
can be very clear
能夠非常的清楚
we now know more and more
我們現在越來越了解
what kind of creatures are we
我們是什麼樣的生物
our surroundings
我們對我們周圍的環境
I know more and more where the same
越來越知道是哪裡有相同
Where is the difference
哪裡不同
Our Taiwan can live such a good life
我們過的台灣能夠過這麼好的日子
what can we do
到底我們何得何能
Why can we communicate with many advanced countries
為什麼我們可以跟很多先進國家
Enjoy the relative advantages and disadvantages of material life
享受相對優惡的物質生活
What exactly is collective intelligence?
到底集體智慧是什麼發生的
can we see our future
我們能不能看到我們的未來
When I was designing my own general education course
我在設計我自己的通識課的時候
In fact, many things about Taiwan
其實是對台灣的很多事情
i don't have an answer
我沒有一個答案
But I guess it's all of us
可是我猜應該是由我們大家
Let's plan together how we will go in the future
一起來規劃我們未來要怎麼走
it may not have a certain right and wrong
它可能沒有一定的對和錯
But as long as we all agree
可是只要我們大家都同意
What direction should we go
什麼方向我們應該要做
For example, Taiwan has no personnel
譬如說台灣沒有人員
Then do we want to increase the price or not?
那我們到底要漲價 不漲價
if no price increase
如果不漲價的話
how do we use our people
我們要怎麼樣使用我們的人員
Then we don't lack water resources
那我們沒有缺乏水資源
Most of the water on our mountains now
我們現在大部分山上的水
Once down, it will flow to Hainan.
一下下來就流到海南頭去
How do we use our water resources
我們怎麼樣使我們的水資源
be used with caution
能夠謹慎的使用
i think these things
我覺得這些事情
It's not absolutely right or wrong
它其實沒有絕對對錯
But maybe we have to find it together
可是可能是要大家一起找到
way of living together
共同生活的方式
ok thank you all
好 謝謝大家
I see you need some water
看你要喝點水
ok the rest of the time i think
好 剩下的時間我想
asked a lot of questions
提了很多問題
Some secretly suggested that I have no answer
有的有的 暗議 我的沒答案
so do it again
所以再做
Any questions or comments welcome
有任何問題或者comments歡迎
Thank you Professor Chen Zhuting for your speech
謝謝陳珠婷教授的演講
I heard and learned a lot
聽到學了很多
Just mentioned that there are 23 million people in Taiwan
剛剛提到說台灣2300萬人
We should have enough food now
我們現在糧食應該夠
Because it can feed so many people
因為可以養活這樣多的人
If there are more in the future, it may not be enough.
那將來多了可能就不夠來怎麼樣
In fact, our food shortage in Taiwan is serious
事實上我們台灣現在糧食是嚴重不足的
Because our autonomy is only 32%
因為我們自主力只有32%
Most are imported
大部分都是靠進口的
if not imported
如果不是進口
We can't actually live that many people
我們事實上活不了這麼多人
something went wrong
早就出問題了
The energy part is
能源的部分的話就是
I think we should really save
我是覺得說我們的確是應該決省
what should be raised
應該漲價什麼那些
both but perhaps more importantly
都是但是說不定更重要的是
We should develop the energy of the future
我們應該研發未來的能源
R & D technology
研發技術
How about in the future there will be
那怎麼樣將來在全世界有
That is to say, there are technologies available to others
就是說有技術提供給人家
and then get energy harvested elsewhere
然後在別的地方得到能源收穫回來
e.g. priesthood energy
譬如說聖職能源
that may be my new technology
那或者是我新的技術
technology is then transferred to other countries
然後技術轉移給其他的國家
What about getting the first prize in our economy?
得到我們經濟的首得還是怎麼樣的
similar to this one
類似這一種
that now
那現在
More influential when dealing together
一起成交的時候比較影響力
we are now that
我們現在那個
Research and development related to energy in Taiwan
台灣有關能源的研發
The money spent is really
花的經費實在是
really too little too little
真的是太少太少
So this is a bad phenomenon
所以這個是很糟糕的一個現象
Then we didn't have oil
那本來我們沒有石油
That's not much coal
那煤炭也不多
Other energy natural gas liquids are rare
其他能源天然氣液很少
that is no way
那是沒辦法
because we don't have that many resources
因為我們沒有那麼多資源
But our brain power should be able to blossom
但是我們的腦力應該是可以開花
new technologies can be developed
可以發展新的技術出來
This is our hope for the future
這個才是我們未來的希望
But this aspect is obviously less thoughtful.
但是這方面顯然琢磨比較少一點
probably should have said
可能應該是說
We are now 2300
我們現在2300
Three million people live as if we have enough resources
三百萬人過的日子一副好像我們的資源很夠的樣子
I don't look too worried
也不太擔心的樣子
Although most people talked about what fuel and electricity will increase
大部分人雖然說講了什麼油電要漲的是什麼
everyone get nervous
大家緊張一下
But in the way of life, it seems that there is no shortage of resources
可是在過日子的樣子好像一副資源沒有不足的樣子
This is actually
這個其實是
No, Taiwan is really
不 台灣現在真的是
Often when an idea comes up
常常一個想法提出來的時候
There are actually many different voices, right?
不同的聲音其實很多嘛 對不對
we all know a lot
我們都知道很多
So in terms of social decision-making
所以在整個社會決策上面來講
There are many places where there are actually bottlenecks
有很多地方事實上是有瓶頸
In terms of planning
在規劃上面來講
I often say three words
我常常提三句話
Also for the board of education
也是為了教育委員會提的
I said there are a lot of talents in Taiwan
我說台灣人才很多啊
few teams
團隊很少
Then there are a lot of jobs in Taiwan
然後台灣的工作很多
but few ideas
可是理念很少
Taiwan has many plans
台灣的計劃很多
This is for us probably
這針對我們大概
This research unit
這研究單位講的
But the cumulative effect is little
可是累積的效果很少
So it seems that nothing has changed and accumulated like this
所以好像就沒有變累積成這樣
a more collective common wisdom
一個比較集體的共同智慧
Might be when I'm thinking about this aspect of the speech
可能是我在思考這一方面的演講的時候
An idea that is always in my heart
常常放在心裡的一個想法
no absolute answer
沒有絕對的答案
But we are in a relatively negative cycle
可是我們落在了一個比較負面的循環裡頭
when jumping out of the vortex
要跳出漩渦的時候
Sometimes I feel a little weak
有的時候會有一點點好像有氣無力的感覺
But it seems that we really want to be together
不過好像還是要大家真的要一起
especially us
尤其是我們
I think our academia may
我想我們學界說不定
should do something more
應該再做一點事情吧
too broad
太廣泛了
However, the average human being is also very flexible.
不過一般人類的彈性也很大
So can withstand pressure
所以可以耐壓性
Can't beat the whole civilization
拗不過就整個文明
just like loss
就像剛剛就是loss
But actually another thing
不過其實另外一個事情
It's you, the whole world is 7 billion
就是你全世界即便是70億
But only about 1% of people
可是大概只有1%的人
may want to use or his resources
可能想用的或他的資源
maybe more than 90%
可能就超過90%
It's a very balanced
這是一個很平衡的
so you say carrying capacity
所以你說carrying capacity
what is this place called
這個地方就是那個叫什麼
weight ratio
權重比例
an african man
一個非洲的人
resources consumed by him
他的所消耗的資源
resources consumed by a civilized nation
跟一個文明國家消耗的資源
It's very different
就是相差非常的多
Saved people after a long time
很久又救人家
What percentage of the world's talent is the United States
美國人才占全世界的比例多少
But the energy he consumes may be 670 percent
可是他消耗的能量可能是百分之六十七十
seems to be usually capable
好像通常是有本事
I feel free to take other people's things first and use them.
覺得自由本事能把別人的東西先搶來用的在做
this may change
這個也許會變化
hello mr chen
陳老師你好
so i want to ask
所以我想要請問一下
Because this topic is about sustainable civilization
因為這個而言講的題目是關於永續文明
sustainable civilization
永續文明
Then I want to ask
那我想請問一下就是
As for Mr. Chen's vision for both energy and human beings
就陳老師對於不管是能源或是人類的願景
maybe not to the whole world
就也許沒有到整個全世界
At least in Taiwan about energy
至少在我們台灣就關於能源
or about our entire vision of using energy or matter
或是關於我們整個使用能源或是物質上的願景
Then I would like to ask Professor Chen
那我想請問一下陳教授這樣
Thanks
謝謝
with just
跟剛剛
the same as the one mentioned
那位所提的一樣
In fact, some things have no definite answer
其實有些東西是沒有確定的答案
but in the race
可是在賽跑
For example, new personnel and new materials
譬如說新的人員新的材料
currently running
目前有在跑
Is that the person in the immediate situation
那是不是人在即時的情況之下
find the answer
找到解答
Then solve it more effectively
然後比較有效的解決掉
For example, how much
譬如說多少
How many problems are solved
解決掉多少的問題
This is actually in a situation where there is no standard answer
這個事實上是在一個沒有標準答案的情況之下
side by side
一面做一面看
For example, in terms of banning people in Taiwan,
譬如說像台灣在封人使用方面
Most experts don't think that's an effective solution to the problem
大部分的專家不認為那是一個有效可以解決問題的辦法
How many percent can the Sun people solve?
那太陽人方面可以解決到百分之幾
seems to have an estimate
好像有一個估計
But after we made the Taiwan Sunman version,
可是我們台灣太陽人版做出來以後
Most of them are exported
大部分是外銷了
I'm useless
自己沒有用
The reason is to cooperate
原因是要配合的
Technology didn't play well together
技術並沒有配合得很好
Then under the condition of relatively high price
然後在價錢相對高的情況之下
At least not currently
至少目前使用並不是
Taiwan does not use much solar energy
台灣沒有用多少的太陽能
Most of them are exported to other places
大部分都外銷到別的地方去
Especially in Europe, we export a lot
尤其是歐洲我們外銷的很多
Like this thing actually it
像這件事情其實它
Of course there are possible solutions
當然有可能解決的途徑
The most direct one is
那最直接的一個就是
Should Taiwan Confront Nuclear Energy?
台灣要不要面對核能
Then this one takes the lead in our entire social hierarchy
那這個在我們的整個社會層次領頭
is a knotted problem
是一個打結的問題
There is currently no good solution
目前沒有很好的解決方法
so i say something like this
所以我說像這種事情
It's a lot like our own life sometimes
它很像我們一個人的人生有些時候
You sometimes have to face making a decision
你有時候必須要面對做一個決定
then it may be a painful decision
那它也許是一個痛苦的決定
may be take it or leave it
可能是接受或放棄
can be a decision
都可能是一個決定
But it's at least a decision
可是它至少是一個決定
Then we sometimes make this kind of decision in life.
那我們有時候人生也會做這種決定
After doing it, I will continue to move forward
做了以後就還是會繼續往前走
Instead of just stopping at one location
而不是說就停在一個位置上
Then everyone seems to be arguing
然後大家好像吵得不可開箱
That's the material
那倒是材料上面
I think from the perspective of my chemistry
我覺得以我學化學的角度
We have a lot of resources that can be used for new creations
我們有很多的資源是可以再做新的創造的
I think it's cute
這我認為還是可人的
People are more critical in terms of technology
人員在技術上面來講比較關鍵
I dare not speak directly
我就不敢直接講
For example, let’s talk about a few more likely to be compatible with our hopes.
譬如說幾個比較有可能我們寄望的合容合
Is it right?
到底是不是合在
Available before 2050
2050年之前就能夠用得到
Seems like a big question mark so far
好像到目前還是一個大的問號
If it cannot be developed effectively before 2050
如果2050年之前不能夠很有效的發展出來的話
Opportunity to express
表示合容合的機會
the one that cost a lot of money
那個花很多錢的
And not all countries can't use it
而且不是所有的國家都用不住
Is it forcing some countries to engage in nuclear fission?
是不是就逼得有些國家非去做核分裂
Taiwan must at least import oil
那台灣至少要進口石油
So this probably won't work
所以這個大概跑不了
We don't have such personnel here
我們這邊是沒有這樣的人員的
So maybe you need to think about it this way
所以大概需要去用這種方式去想
The other BIOMASS now
其他的那個BIOMASS現在
It also involves arguing about whether food should be used in this way
又牽涉到在吵說是應不應該用這樣子使用食物
So I think this kind of thing needs to be done to make a clarification.
所以我想這類東西都要做下來做一個釐清
Why did I emphasize on seeing things from the perspective of science majors?
我剛剛為什麼特別強調科學專業的角度看事情
Seeing things differently from a non-scientific perspective
和非科學專業的角度看事情不太一樣
But it's not the same. If you use the opposite
可是不太一樣如果是用對立的
a lot of trouble
很多問題就很麻煩
But if it is used to talk about it
可是如果是用做下來談的話
I think maybe we can find some ways to improve
我覺得也許可以找到一些可以改進的途徑
I'm a little bit more optimistic about resources than people
我對資源比對人員稍微樂觀一點點
Because the resource actually should be full on Earth in some way
因為資源事實上在地球上應該還滿有一些方式
You can use time in exchange for conditioning
可以去用時間換取來調理
The words of the staff are not enough
人員的話說不夠了以後
Immediately the industry is like Taiwan's industry, it should be affected immediately
馬上工業就像台灣的工業應該是馬上就受影響吧
I believe that economy will be affected immediately
我相信那個經濟馬上就受影響
Of course, there is a problem involved here, that is,
當然這裡牽涉到一個問題就是說
What kind of economic indicators should Taiwan use?
台灣應不應該用怎麼樣的經濟指標
to plan for growth
去規劃做成長
So what is the problem
那這個問題到底是
should or should not
應該還是不應該
It also apparently has a different answer
它也顯然有不同的答案
some people think that means
有些人就覺得就是說
If there is no economic growth
如果不做經濟成長的話
How can we live a better life
我們日子怎麼樣能夠過得更好
But the economy is doing better
可是經濟過得更好
Is everyone sure
是不是大家一定
an ideal society
是一個比較理想的社會
I'm not sure either
我也不太確定
So questions like this are usually on the table in Taiwan
所以像這類問題平常在台灣的檯面上
less people talk about it
比較少人去談它
Your question may not be able to be provided by me alone
你的問題其實可能沒辦法由我一個人來提供意見
I can tell you simply
我只比較簡單的可以告訴你
From the perspective of certain money-paying technologies of science
以科學的某些出錢的技術來看的話
We need to be on certain material resources
我們要在某些物質的資源上面
to move forward
要往前在
Advanced technology takes a few more steps
先進的科技上面多走幾步路
still have a chance
還有機會
this is no problem
這個沒有問題
I dare not speak
人員我就不敢講
I don't know if Teacher Wang treats the personnel right?
我不知道王老師對人員是不是
is there any way
有沒有辦法
There may be some more here
這個在座可能還有一些
This expert may have a better answer than me
這專家可能會比我有更好的答案
I will compare
我就比較
I think it's almost time
我想時間也差不多了
we are very happy today
我們今天很高興
Professor Chen gave us a very
陳教授給我們做一個非常
widely
廣泛
Then it also caused everyone to go back and think about it.
然後也引發大家這個回去好好省思的一些
some problems
一些問題
ok thank you very much
好非常謝謝
Thank you Professor Chen
謝謝陳教授
thank you all
謝謝大家
thank you very much
非常謝謝